<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of church gouernment Dedicated to the high Court of Parliament. Wherein, the church gouernment established in England, is directly proued to be consonant to the word of God, and that subiects ought of dutie to conforme themselues to the state ecclesiasticall. Together with, a defence of the crosse in baptisme; as it is vsed in our Church, being not repugnant to the word: and by a consequent, the brethren which are silenced, ought to subscribe vnto it, rather then to burie their talents in the ground. By Iohn Doue, Doctour of Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Dove, John, 1560 or 61-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845723</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845723</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10643</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10643)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1446:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of church gouernment Dedicated to the high Court of Parliament. Wherein, the church gouernment established in England, is directly proued to be consonant to the word of God, and that subiects ought of dutie to conforme themselues to the state ecclesiasticall. Together with, a defence of the crosse in baptisme; as it is vsed in our Church, being not repugnant to the word: and by a consequent, the brethren which are silenced, ought to subscribe vnto it, rather then to burie their talents in the ground. By Iohn Doue, Doctour of Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Dove, John, 1560 or 61-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for Henry Rockit, and and are to bee sold by Iohn Hodgets in Paules Churchyeard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In part a reply to: Bradshaw, William.  A shorte treatise, of the crosse in baptisme.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618. --  Shorte treatise, of the crosse in baptisme --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cross, Sign of the --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10643:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10643:1"/>
            <p> A DEFENCE OF Church Gouernment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedicated to the high Court of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN, THE CHVRCH GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> is directly proued to be conſonant to the word of God, and that ſubiects <hi>ought of dutie to conforme themſelues to the</hi> ſtate Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>Together with, A DEFENCE OF THE CROSSE IN Baptiſme; as it is vſed in our Church, being not repugnant <hi>to the word: and by a conſequent, the brethren which are</hi> ſilenced, ought to ſubſcribe vnto it, rather <hi>then to burie their Talents in</hi> the ground.</p>
            <p>By IOHN DOVE, Doctour of Diuinity.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Rockit,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Hodgets</hi> in Pauls Church yeard. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10643:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE firſt Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of conformitie to the ſtate Eccleſiasticall.</item>
               <item>Of Elderſhip.</item>
               <item>Of Dioceſan Biſhops.</item>
               <item>Of Cathedrall Churches.</item>
               <item>Of Lord Biſhops, and eccleſiaſticall perſons exerciſing ciuill authoritie.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10643:2"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Lords ſpirituall and temporall of <hi>the vpper houſe, with the Knights and Burgeſſes of the lower houſe, aſſembled</hi> in the high Court of Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="defense">
            <div type="part">
               <head> Of conformitie to the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe the wiſedome of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſembly, to weigh our reaſons, not onely in the ballance of mans wit, but alſo in the ſkales of the ſancturarie, why this conformiture is required. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>beſeeching vs as brethren in the name of our Lord Ieſus Christ, that wee all ſpeake one thing, that there bee no diſſentions among vs, that wee bee knit together in one minde and iudgement:</hi> commendeth it vnto vs as a neceſſary rule of Eccleſiaſticall politie, for the better eſtabliſhing of this conſent in doctrine, the ſpeedy cutting off of all iarres and diſcenſions, the faſt knitting and vniting of mindes and iudgements: vppon this ground and warrant other ſtates haue vrged their Preachers to conforme themſelues to the State vnder which they liued. And ſeeing by this rule apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall it cannot ſtand with the peace and good eſtate of any Church whatſoeuer, to permit ſuch among them as are not of them, and to tollerate ſuch in their Miniſterie as
<pb facs="tcp:10643:3"/> are aduerſaries: to their lawes and conſtitutions: much more then is conformitie ſo grounded vpon Scripture, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by example of other Churches, deemed by the godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and approued by the wiſeſt, to be no leſſe needfull in this preſent ſciſme and rent of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then was pitch for the Arke of <hi>Noah</hi> floating vpon the water, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ruines of the Temple expoſed to the iniury of wind and weather, without which the one could not but preſently ſinke, and the other not long continue.</p>
               <p>And, for as much as ſome fewe among vs in their priuate opinions diſſent from vs, not onely godly politie teacheth, and Chriſtian humilitie requireth, but alſo the Lawe of God which is of higheſt authority preſcribeth and commandeth, that theſe fewe ſhould ſubmit themſelues to the wiſedome of the State, rather then the whole ſtate ſhould yeelde, and giue place to the contradiction of thoſe priuate ſpirits. When certaine brethren at <hi>Antioch</hi> varied about circumſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 1.</note> they were ouerſwayed by the cenſure of the Councell helde at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to whom the hearing of ſuch differences, and diſciding of ſuch coutrouerſies, did of right belong, but the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence of the Councel gaue no way at all to thoſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And Saint <hi>Paule</hi> hauing ſpoken of the ceremonie deuiſed by <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> the Church, and vſed in his time, in prayer and propheſie, <hi>that men ſhould be bare, and women couered:</hi> noteth them for contentious perſons which oppoſe themſelues againſt this ceremonie, alledging: that it once being approued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into the Church, ought not to bee called into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>vel to nomine,</hi> becauſe the Church had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, when hee ſaith: <hi>If any man liſt to bee contentious, wee haue no ſuch cuſtome among vs, nor the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the better inlarging of this point, that I may not inſtance in the Turkiſh Gouernment, which ſuffereth no queſtion to be moued againſt Eccleſiaſticall riſes, but endeth all ſuch controuerſies by the ſword, neither yet in the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> Church, which admitteth none to any place in the
<pb facs="tcp:10643:3"/> miniſtery without ſubſcription and oath to the reformation of <hi>Angsburge;</hi> nor in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their Clergie to maintaine the doctrine concluded in the councell of <hi>Trent:</hi> the Church of <hi>Geneua,</hi> whoſe lawes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See the laws of the booke of Geneua. Chap.</hi> 1.</note> and gouernment our brethren would impoſe vpon vs, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he onely paterne of holineſſe, and example of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reformation, inioyneth all their Miniſters before their admition, not onely to make open proteſtation, that they doe receiue and maintaine the doctrine approoued in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> but ſimply, and abſolutely to ſweare, that they will keepe the Eccleſiaſticall ordinances, which are paſſed and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>in the forme of their oath.</hi>
                  </note> ordeined by the ſmall, great, and generall councells of that Citie. By which law and practiſe of theirs, it is a cleare caſe, that with them there is no reſpect of priuate mens o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, no ſatisfaction to bee yeelded to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, no conference or diſputation granted with men of contrary iudgements. But, it muſt be held <hi>pro conceſſo,</hi> for a concluſion or principle already proued, that all their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are according to Gods word, and of that vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truth, that they may not be argued, ſifted, or contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</note> Finally, if there ariſe any difference concerning do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which hath not beene already reconciled, it is inacted by their lawes, that the Miniſters ſhall be called to a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; if then it cannot receiue an end, the Magiſtrates ſhall interpoſe their authority, and ſo proceede to a finall deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And for the better ſtrengthening of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, it is further inacted, that all oppoſition againſt their ordinances, ſhall be held for an hainous crime, called by the title of rebellion againſt Eccleſiaſtical lawes: &amp; it is ſet down as puniſhable among the notorious crimes of hereſie, ſciſme, blaſphemy, ſimony, bribery, periury, and drunkenneſſe, The puniſhment to be inflicted vppon Miniſters thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling, is depoſition from their miniſtery, and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt Eccleſiaſticall orders, in what perſons ſoeuer, after three admonitions, is cenſured by excommunication. Yet I deſire that no ſiniſter or vncharitable conſtruction ſhould be made hereof, as if a ſtate ſhould vrge them which
<pb facs="tcp:10643:4"/> feele any the ſmalleſt check in their tender conſciences with ſhipwrack of conſcience, raſhly to ſubſcribe vnto that which they doe not approue, or for worldly reſpects, to allow of that whereof they cannot ſatisfie &amp; well informe themſelues. For albeit the ſtate, which is well aduiſed, hath ſufficient warrant to impoſe, yet the bare authority of the ſtate, is no warrant vnto them to obey, which be not yet reſolued, but ſtand in doubt, becauſe they muſt build vpon this ground of the Apoſtle, that be the thing in it ſelfe neuer ſo lawfull, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, it is ſinne.</hi> But onely I exhort them better to inſtruct and informe their weake conſciences, which if they cannot, or will not doe, the imputation of this ſchiſme muſt not be <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> laide vpon the ſtate, which is well aduiſed, but vpon their weakneſſe, which will not be perſwaded when they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, which are men wedded to their owne opinions, or that I may ſpeake more mildely of them, which either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or will not reforme their iudgements.</p>
               <p>But for the better ſatisfaction of our Chriſtian brethren, we will not refuſe to yeeld reaſons of our gouernment, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it it hath beene ſo long by law eſtabliſhed: and for the iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of our ſtate, we will by Gods aſsiſtance, proue it in the chapters following, to ſtand with the lawes of the holy Bible. As namely, that the ſtate of Archbiſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, which hath continued among vs euer ſince wee firſt receiued the Goſpel, had their inſtitution from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whereas pariſh Churches are mans inuention: and the gouernment of the Presbitery, is not onely repugnant to the lawes of the holy Scriptures, but alſo preiudiciall to the ſtate of a Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10643:4"/>
               <head>A defence of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment eſtabliſhed in England.</head>
               <head>Of Elderſhip.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll would be in title as high as <hi>Aaron,</hi> all would bee gouernours rather then pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Miniſters; but becauſe the keyes of the Church are not committed vnto all which be of the miniſterie; therfore ſome of our brethren, being diſcontented with the preſent ſtate, make it now a queſtion, whether the Church of right, ought to be ordered by elders, as it is in <hi>Geneua,</hi> or by Dioceſan Lord Biſhoppes, as it is in England? I cannot denie but the gouernment of the Church is committed to Elders in the new Teſtament, where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith: <hi>The elders which rule well, are worthy of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>eſpecially they which labour in the word and doctrine.</hi> But, the diſputation is between vs and our brethren, which ſtand for the elderſhip; whether theſe elders were lay men of trades &amp; worldly vocations, as they be now in <hi>Geneua,</hi> or preachers, &amp; eccleſiaſticall perſons? whether this Elderſhip was an annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or a perpetuall office? whether they ought, their yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, to relinquiſh that office, and ſo to returne to their trades and occupations, as they doe in <hi>Geneua,</hi> or elſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the whole terme of their liues? They alleage for the eſtabliſhing of their laye Presbyterie, that becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth theſe wordes: <hi>especially they which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the word:</hi> therefore two ſortes of Elders are there included, ſome learned and preaching Miniſters, ſome vnlearned, and therefore vnpreaching and ſilent gouernors.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10643:5"/> Therefore, to come to the true conſtruction of this text, and due vnderſtanding of the words, which may be conſonant, and agreeable, both to the analogy of faith, and of that place: the doctrine of the Apoſtle includeth two things: a theſis, or generall concluſion; and afterward a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of that theſis or generall concluſion, by a kinde of <hi>epanorthoſis or reuocation</hi> of himſelfe by a reſtraint and limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that generall doctrine, ſhewing how farre it is to be vnderſtood; as namely, that if they labour in the word and doctrine, they are worthy of double honour: but if they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not in the word, hee vouchſafeth them no double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. So that out of theſe wordes, can be collected no ſuch diſtinction as they doe imagine, of preaching elders, and gouerning elders, which are no preachers, but of gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning elders both of them preachers, one ſort which labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the word, the other which preacheth alſo, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth not in preaching. For, it is one thing to be a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and another thing to labour in preaching. And what it is to labour in preaching, he expoundeth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, where hee ſaith: <hi>I charge thee before God, and the Lord Ieſus Christ, which ſhall iudge the quicke and the dead,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>at his appearing, and in his Kingdome, preach the word, bee inſtant, in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon.</hi> The Greeke word is <hi>(copion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes)</hi> which is as much as to indure the heate and burthen of the day, to take extraordinary paines in the miniſtery. But that the writings of the Apoſtles acknowledge, neither an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, nor lay elders, my reaſons are theſe.</p>
               <p>Becauſe elderſhip is a lawfull miniſtery, therefore it is of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God: but a man which is called of God vnto the miniſterie, may not after the expiration of one yeare, or at his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, be diſcharged of that calling, or by any warrant from men play the Iordan to ſtart backe againe. For, that were with <hi>Demas</hi> to forſake Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> fellowſhippe, and to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 62</note> imbrace this preſent world. This miniſtrie is the Lords huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry; that is, the Lords plough: and, hauing once laid their hands to this plough, if they looke backe, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnfit for the kingdome of God.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10643:5"/>
               <p> God calleth no man, whom he furniſheth not with ſome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> talents, more or fewer, and theſe talents may not ruſt. But <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note> ſuch lay elders haue no talents at all committed vnto them: And therefore I ſay vnto them, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus: They haue no part nor fellowſhippe in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church muſt be ordered accorcing to the precepts <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and examples of holy writ; but wee haue neither example for inſtance, that euer there was, nor precept out of Gods booke for warrant, that euer there may be any ſuch lay el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip. But to the contrary, we abound in examples, and <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</note> haue expreſſe commandements. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> a preacher, calleth himſelfe an elder, and chargeth other elders to feede the flocke. Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> a preacher, calleth himſelfe an elder, in his epiſtle to the elect Lady. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to feede the Church of God which he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note> with his blood. And to <hi>Titus,</hi> he giueth charge that he appoint ouer euery Citie Elders, and hee ſheweth that by ſuch elders he meaneth Biſhops, which muſt be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort with wholeſome doctrine, and to conuince them which ſay againſt it.</p>
               <p>Deacons which be of an inferiour calling in the Church, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> muſt not be lay men, but able to preach: much more then Elders which haue an higher office, and as they be their ſelues conſecrated by impoſition of hands, ſo haue their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to lay their handes vpon Deacons, and conſecrate them. But concerning Deacons, the Apoſtles ſpeake in this manner: <hi>Chooſe you out</hi> 7. <hi>men of honeſt report, full of the holy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Ghoſt, and wiſedome, whom we may appoint to this buſineſſe, and we will giue our ſelues continually to prayer, and the miniſtration of the word.</hi> In theſe words: <hi>full of wiſedome:</hi> they meane not world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but heauenly wiſedome, which is the knowledge of the Scriptures: but whoſoeuer hath ſuch fulneſſe of knowledge and vnderſtanding of the Bible, is very able to preach. And where the Apoſtles ſay: <hi>we wil giue our ſelues continually to prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, &amp; miniſtration of the word:</hi> it doth not follow that therefore the deacons being appointed to their office of Deaonſhip,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10643:6"/> did wholy neglect preaching, and the miniſtration of the word, no more, then that they did alſo giue ouer praying, which is here mentioned in the imployment of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as well as preaching, (for then had they beene repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.) And that after they were called to be Deacons, they did alſo preach, and miniſter the ſacraments: it appeareth by the examples of <hi>Stephen,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> which both preached, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 35. 38. 50.</note> and baptiſed. Neither can a man of ſober iudgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſuch an idle opinion of the Apoſtles, that they would haue admitted them to that office, by that great ſolemnity of prayer and impoſition of hands, if they ſhould haue beene eſtranged from the miniſterie, and wholly attended vpon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and beene but gatherers of almes.</p>
               <p>God which hath eſtabliſhed kingdomes, and ordained ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Princes to be ſupreame gouernours in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, by his word, cannot ſo much croſſe his owne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as to appoint in the ſame word, ſuch a conſiſtory, or ſtate of eccleſiaſticall gouernment, as may not ſtand with the ſtate of a kingdome. As for the gouernment of Biſhops vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King, it hath alwaies vpheld the ſtate of a kingdom, and maintained the ſoueraigne authority of Princes, as hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Scepter and Crowne immediately from God, and not from the people, that they are not to be depoſed, nor cenſured by the people. But contrariwiſe, the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and their fauourers, both by their doctrine, and alſo by practiſe, make all Kings ſubiect to the people, and by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, to the Conſiſtorie to be puniſhed and depriued by them, becauſe they are the Magiſtrates which are choſen by the people, and for the people, &amp; the authority of the people is executed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And for the better proofe of this aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I wil produce ſome writings of the presbyterians the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. The Scottiſh Conſiſtorian hath theſe words following: <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eucan: de iure regni apùd Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos.</note> 
                  <hi>iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt, vt imporiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cui velit deferat.</hi> It reſteth in the hands of the people, to ſet the Crown vpon whoſe head they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>B. <hi>Nam niſi regem ſuffragijs electum habeamus, vereor nè le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimum habituri ſimus.</hi> M. <hi>Ego quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> idem iſlud vereor.</hi> No man is a lawfull King, but by election of the people.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10643:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Nam, &amp; quem nes Venetorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vocamus, is nihil aliud est, qùám rex legitimus.</hi> He whom we we call the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> is nothing elſe, but a lawfull King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leges igitùr hâc dè cauſâ inuentae ſunt à populis, regeſque co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acti, non ſuâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n iudicijs licentiâ, ſed quod populus in ſe dediſſet iure, vti.</hi> For this cauſe lawes are deùiſed by the people, and Kings conſtrained, not to vſe their own liberty in the ſeate of Iuſtice, but that whereunto the people hath reſtrained them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sit, quando ita vis, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>në<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> populum vt leges ſerat, &amp; perferat, ſint reges velut tabularioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> custodes.</hi> The making of lawes is onely in the power of the people, kings are but as it were keepers of the records.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vides opinor, quantam vno verſu des principi licentiam: nempè, vt quod velit ipſe, dicet lex, quod nolit non dicat. Id ſi ſemèl recipia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, non proderit bonas leges condere, quae principem bonum officij ſui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oneant, malum circumſcribant. Immo, vt dica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apertiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, nullas omninò<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leges habere praeſtaret, quàm liberum latrocinium, atquè eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am honoratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſub legis praetextu tolerari.</hi> M. <hi>Certè, non modo poteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> legum iubendaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed etiàm eas interpretandi, regiabſtuliſt:</hi> As kings may not be makers of lawes, ſo they may not be truſted with the expoſition of lawes, for then it were all one as if no good lawes were made, which may put a good Prince in mind of his duty, &amp; compell an euil Prince to doe his dutie, becauſe they will wreſt them to their owne purpoſe. And ſo robberie ſhal not onely be free, but alſo rewarded and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder the colour and pretence of lawe.</p>
               <p>Concerning ſuch Princes as behaue not themſelues well in their gouernment: <hi>Deo &amp; hominibus habendes inimicos, eoſqùe in luporum, aliorumnè noxiorum animalium genere, potiùs quàm ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, habendos putem, quae qui alit, &amp; ſibi pernicie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alit, &amp; alijs &amp; qui occidit, non ſibi modo, ſed publicè vniuerſis prodeſt. Interfectori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus autèm praemia decarni non ab vniuerſo tantùm populo, ſed à ſm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis: quemadmodùm vulg ò fieri ſolet ijs qui lupos aut vrſas occide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> They be enemies to God and man: Wolues, who ſo kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, benefiteh the common wealth, and is to be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as he that killeth Wolues, Bares, and ſuch harmful beaſts. And what is this leſſe then which the conſpirators of <hi>Rome</hi> do hold it meritorious to murther Princes.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10643:7"/>
               <p> Againe, ſaith this Preſbyterian: <hi>Quemadmodùm in primis regibus vſquè, ad Kennethum</hi> 3 <hi>qui primus regnum in ſuâ familiâ ſtabiliuit, perſpicua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est quae fuerit potestas populi in regibus creandis, &amp; in ordinem redigendis: ità neceſſe eſt vt is aut populo inuito id fecerit, aut à perſuaſo impetrauerit. Perrò, ſi ceëgit populum ſibi parere, populus quoquè vbi primum caeperit ſuis viribus confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, violentum illud imperium poterit excutere, cùm à regibus &amp; populo recepta iura pronuncient, &amp; natura clamet, quicquid per vim fiat ſimili vi ſolui poſſe Si tu mecum ex conuentu agas, quid cauſae eſt, quin ego ex aduerſo eas cauſas ponam, cur pacta &amp; conuenta ſolui poſſint?</hi> What power the people hath both in ſetting vp kings, and ruling them after they be eſtabliſhed, <hi>Kennethus</hi> the third, is an example, which firſt eſtabliſhed the kingdome in his own family. If by violence he compelled the people to yeeld vnto it, by the ſame violence they may free themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if by their conſent, they may pretend cauſe enough to reuerſe that whereunto they gaue conſent. And what is this but the doctrine of the Papiſts, that faith with heretikes is not to be held?</p>
               <p>To them which alledge that wee muſt pray for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though they be wicked, and therefore not lift vp our <note place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> hands againſt them; he anſwereth. <hi>Nèc ſlatim, ſi promalis principibus orandum eſt, hinc allegare debemus corum vitia non eſſe punienda: non magis quam latronum, prò quibus etiam orare iubemur, nec ſi bono principi parendum eſt, ideò malo non eſt reſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> We are bound to pray for wicked Princes, in ſuch ſort as for theeues: we muſt pray for them both, and puniſh them both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod autem àd Caligulam, Neronem, Domitianum &amp; reliquos eius generis tyrannos attinet: cur violats iuris diuini &amp; humani poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebeant exigi, nihil hic apùd Paulum habes, qui de ipſâ magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratuum potestate, non dè malis ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è poteſtatem eam gerentibus diſſerat. Nec, ſi ad Pauli regulam id genus tyrannorum examines, omninò magiſtratus erunt.</hi> As for <hi>Caligula, Nero, Domitian,</hi> and ſuch tyrants, it ſtandeth with <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine that they may be puniſhed for their offences. For he diſputeth onely of the lawful autoritie of the magiſtrates not of wicked magiſtrates
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10643:7"/> which abuſe their authoritie. Neither according to Saint <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine are ſuch Kings to be held for Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vt cunque negare non poſſunt: aulici adulatoras carnificis functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem pariem eſſe muneris publici, &amp; fortaſſe etiam regij, vel ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum regum testimonio, qui quoties aliquis è ministus publicis viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſe, ſuamquè maiestatem, &amp; corpus violari queruntur.</hi> The flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Courtiers cannot denie, but that the office of the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth belong to the King, witnes the Kings themſelues, which when their Catchpoles, and hangmen receiue any wrong, doe complaine that their owne perſon is in them wronged, and their princely Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Quid tande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e ſcripturis profers cur liceat tyrannos impunè occidere?</hi> B. <hi>Primùm id affero, quod quùm diſerte praeceptum ſit de ſcelere, &amp; ſceleratis à medio tollendis, ſinè vllâ exceptione gradus aut ordinis nuſquàm tamen in ſaeris literis tyrannis magis quàm priuatis eſt cautum.</hi> Hauing a generall commandement out of Gods word, to put to death wicked men, without reſpect of any degree or order in particular, tyrants haue no more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge then priuate men, and therefore, according to his word, it is lawfull to kill tyrants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rationem excogitarunt Canonistae quá &amp; ſcelera plecterentur, &amp; Papa tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacro ſanctus &amp; inuiolatus haberetur. Aliud enim Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, aliud illius hominis qui Papa eſſet, ius exiſtimabant, &amp;c.</hi> Wee may diſtinguiſh betweene the Kings perſon and his office, to puniſh him as he is a man offending, ſetting a ſide his place, and ſo not the King, but the malefactor is chaſtiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nos contendimus idem ius reges habere in multitudinem quod illi in ſingulos e multitudine habent.</hi> The people haue ioyntly the ſame authoritie ouer the King, which the King hath ouer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſeuerall perſon among the people.</p>
               <p>The French Conſiſtorians write in this manner: <hi>Subditi</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vindiciae contra ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannos.</note> 
                  <hi>non tenentur regibus obedire, ſiquid aduerſùs legem Dei imperent.</hi> Subiects are not bound to obey Kings, if they command any thing contrary to Gods word. In which aſſertion, firſt they <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt: </seg>1</label> make the ſubiects to be both the plaintiues, and the Iudges betweene their King and themſelues, whether he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded any thing againſt Gods word or no? ſo that it ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10643:8"/> be an eaſie matter for them at their pleaſure to diſcharge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of all dutie and obedience to the King. Secondly, they deceiue the ſimple reader by a fallacie, for, the ambiguitie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe words: <hi>Si quid aduerſus legem dei imperant,</hi> If they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand any thing contrary to Gods word. For, the queſtion is, whether they meane onely in that particular thing which is againſt Gods word, the King is not to be obeyed, or elſe, that in nothing he is to be obeyed, becauſe he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſome one thing repugnant to the law of God? In this laſt ſenſe, it is by them vnderſtood, as appeareth by the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which are theſe: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſallus ſe Domino ſuperiori iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento diuincit, ſic &amp; Rex, ex legis diuinae precepto ſe imperaturum iurat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſallus deniquè niſi iuſiurandum ſeruat, feedum committit, ipſoque iure ſe omni praerogatiuâ priuat. Rex quoque ſi deum negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat &amp;c. ipſo iure regnum committit, &amp; èx facto plerumque amittit. Duplex autem foedus in regum inaugurations legimus, primum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp; regem &amp; populum, vt eſſet populus Dei populus, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum vero inter regem &amp; populum, vt bene obtemperanti benè obtemperaretur.</hi> The vaſſall is bound to his Lord by an oath, and the King ſweareth that hee will rule according to Gods word: if the vaſſal keepeth not his oath, he forfeiteth his eſtate, ſo if the King breake his oath, hee forfeiteth his Crowne. There is a double couenant at a Kings Coronation, the firſt betweene God on the one ſide, and the King with the people on the other ſide, that the people ſhall be Gods people: the ſecond betweene the King and the people, that the people ſhall be faithfull ſubiects no longer then the King ſhal conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a good King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Populus ſi regem non coercet, culpâ tenebitur, quià correi ſunt. Licet Iſràels ſi Rex legem Dei Eccleſiamne euertat, reſiſtere: nèc id</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vindicïae contra ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannos</note> 
                  <hi>modo, verum nifecerit, eiuſdem criminis tonebitur, &amp; eandem poena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> luet. Reſiſtat vero verbo ſi verbo oppugnabitur, vi ſi vi, arte inquàm &amp; marte, quin et dolo bono ſi bono, cùm nihilinterſit vbi iuſtum bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Quſt: </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>ſuſceperis, vtrum aperte pugues an èx inſidijs.</hi> It is lawfull for the people to reſiſt the King which impugneth Gods law, or his Church, and vnles they doe reſiſt him, they ſhall be acceſſarie as he is principall, and incurre the ſame puniſhment which is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10643:8"/> due vnto him. If he deale by ſword or word, they muſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues againſt him with the ſame weapons. For as much as the warre which in that cauſe they doe wage againſt him is iuſt, it maketh no matter whether they vſe open warre and hoſtilitie, or ſecret ſlight and politie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nemo rex naſcitur, nemo per ſe rex eſt, nemo abſqùe populo reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vindic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe contra ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannos,</note> 
                  <hi>poteſt, populus per ſè eſſe poteſt, &amp;c.</hi> No man is borne to a kingdome, no man is of himſelfe à King, no man can raigne but by the fauour of the people, but the people are abſolute <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt: </seg>3</label> of themſelues, the people is in time before the king, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Kings are ordained, &amp; authorized by the people, and in ſuch kingdomes as are haereditarie, the child may not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed his Father, vnles he haue the approbation of the people. <hi>Quùm reges a populo conſtituantur, vniuerſus populus rege prior eſt &amp;c,</hi> Seeing kings are appointed by the people, the whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is aboue the king, his authoritie being deriued from them, he is vnder them as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was vnder <hi>Putifer, Daniel</hi> vnder <hi>Nabuchadnazer.</hi> The king is but a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth as a ſhipmaſter to the honour of the ſhip. Whatſoeuer accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the king by wars, or by his Exchequor, he muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for it to the people, as a Merchants factour is to his. Mr: Let the people forſake their king, he wil be a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible perſon in the eyes of all men, when they ſhall put him from his dominion ouer men, he will be glad to be ſome paedanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fellow, and to vſe his paedagogical authoritie ouer boyes.</p>
               <p>As for our Engliſh Conſiſtorians, they haue theſe words: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>T. C. lib:</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 15. 7. <hi>T. C. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 165. <hi>Admonit:</hi> 2.</note> No ciuil Magiſtrate hath preheminence by ordinary autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to determine of Church cauſes. And, no ciuil magiſtrate in Councels &amp; aſſemblies for Church cauſes, can be chief mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratour, Iudge, or gouernour. And, no ciuil magiſtrate hath ſuch authoritie, as that without his conſent it ſhould not be lawful for Eccleſiaſticall perſons to make any Church orders or ceremonies. For as much therfore as God hath eſtabliſhed kingdomes, but a presbytery and a kingdome cannot both ſtand together, becauſe one ſtanding, the other falleth. They are enemies not onely to Gods ordinance, but alſo to the ſtate of Kings, which goe about to eſtabliſh this Elderſhip in a kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:10643:9"/>
               <head>Of Dioceſan Biſhops.</head>
               <p>MAiſter <hi>Iacob,</hi> in his Booke of reformation obiecteth againſt the ſtate of Biſhops, and Cathedrall Churches, that of right there are no Dioceſan, but onely parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Biſhops, that the authoritie, &amp; iuriſdiction, and rites of a Biſhop, are no other then belongeth to all parſons of pariſh Churches, and conſequently that euery parſon is a Biſhop. That there is no viſible Church miniſteriall, beſides the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches, and that they as depending vpon no other, nor ſubiect to any other, nor parts or members of any other, haue abſolute authoritie and power, as wel of gouernment as of teaching within themſelues, and ſo conſequently, there are no cathederal Churches. And, as one abſurditie being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a thouſand will followe, ſo vpon theſe proemiſes, which without proofe, he taketh for granted, he inferreth theſe fiue concluſions, to the ſlander of our ſtate, as abſord as the proe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes were, That the caſe ſtanding thus: 1. Our Biſhops be no Chriſtians, for (ſaith he) euery Chriſtian is a paſtour, or one of the people, of the people they denye themſelues to be, and paſtours they are not, 2. Being not lawfull Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhops, much leſſe may they be Lord Biſhops. 3. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no lawfull authoritie, nor calling their ſelues, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conferre Eccleſiaſticall orders, and lay handes vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo conſequently our miniſters by them ordered, haue no lawefull miniſterie. 4. That by their meanes wee are defrauded of a mayne point of our ordinarie meanes of ſaluation, which is the true Eccleſieſticall diſcipline.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That in our ſtate Chriſt is robbed and ſpoiled of ſome parts of his kingly and propheticall office, his kingly office being to appoint vs, and his prophetical office, being to teach vs ſolely of himſelfe the true Eccleſiaſticall gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which our Biſhops take from him, and aſcribe vnto men, altering that diſcipline and gouernment, which he alone as king hath appointed, and as a Prophet hath taught in his holy word, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions becauſe they are inferred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe, grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10643:9"/> the grounds being ſhaken, the concluſions will fall of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Therefore let vs come to the examination of theſe grounds, to ſhewe how weake, and vnſufficient a foundation they be to build vpon.</p>
               <p>He impugneth the Church &amp; ſtate of Biſhops, firſt by ſhew of argument, ſecondly by his own idle conceits, vaine coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and imaginations. He maketh ſhew of two arguments, the firſt is this; that the ſtate of Biſhops is a breach of the 2. commandement, and by a conſequent, idolatrie. For in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, thou ſhalt not bow down to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor worſhip it</hi> (ſaith he) are forbidden all meanes being humane inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wherby men would giue honour to the true God. But, one of theſe meanes of diuine worſhip being an humane inuention, he ſaith, to be the ſtate of Biſhops, our Dioceſan, &amp; prouincial Churches vſing gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the miniſteries &amp; offices proper to them. For an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to which argument, I denie the <hi>MINOR</hi> propoſition, which conſiſteth of 2. parts, meanes of diuine worſhip, &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inuention. And becauſe he bringeth no proofe of his <hi>MINOR</hi> being the ſubiect of his diſputation, which all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents ought to doe, I will diſproue it, and each part of it. And firſt, Dioceſan &amp; prouinciall Churches vſing gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their miniſteries, which are of Archbiſhops, &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, were neuer intended by the founders of them, nor v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the officers &amp; miniſters of them, nor held by the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, &amp; maintainers of them, nor conceiued by men of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to be any meanes of diuine worſhip but of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. God can be, and is worſhipped, without theſe, and was worſhipped as ſincerely as now hee is, when they were not, but the Eccleſisſticall ſtate vnder a kingdome cannot be peaceably gouerned without theſe. God is worſhipped alike in <hi>Geneua</hi> and in <hi>England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> though this gouernment and theſe offices, are not in <hi>Geneua</hi> which are in <hi>England.</hi> And God is worſhipped as ſincerely, and as fully, and amplely in our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches as in our cathederal churches, and by ordinarie paſtors, as by Biſhops, ſo that their miniſteries and high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings doe not afforde them any greater or other meanes to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10643:10"/> worſhip God; then they had when they were firſt admitted to be priuate miniſters. But their places, and high callings do ſtrengthen and arme them with authoritie for the better go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of the churches which are committed to them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as being but priuate miniſters, they had no ſuch charge of gouernment. Theſe things therefore are not morall or doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, &amp; therefore belong not vnto worſhip, but politicall, and therefore belong vnto gouernment. And according to the courſe of the holy Bible, that which is politicall &amp; that which is morall, being of ſundrie natures, are to be diſtinguiſhed the one from the other. God in his word eſtabliſhed 3. lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people, one politicall, which did bind the Iewes to the obſeruation of it, but, it was not impoſed vpon other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that they ſhould be bound to receiue it, further then that it might ſtand with the peace, and good of the ſtate. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremoniall which was to abide in force till the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Sauiour, and by his death to be aboliſhed, ſo that now ceremonies vnder the Goſpell doe ceaſe, excepting thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which ſerue, not for worſhip, but decenſie, comlineſſe, and good order, and ſo the primitiue Church did in the dayes of the Apoſtles, and the Church of <hi>Geneua</hi> now doth deuiſe ceremonies, witnes their owne Booke of Lawes, and that all <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> Churches may doe the like, witnes <hi>Caluin, Beza, Vrſinus,</hi> their owne Doctors. The third morall, which containeth rules of Gods worſhip, which was from the beginning, and muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as a patterne of holines to the ende, and bindeth all to the obſeruation of it. But this is no part of that lawe, and all theſe three Lawes differ in nature one from the other. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that ſuch Churches, and Church offices, are not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inuentions, I proue by euident demonſtration. For, the firſt Church miniſteriall that euer was, had ordination from God, which was the Church of the Iewes vnder <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſucceſſours, and that Church was both Dioceſan, and prouinciall, and alſo nationall, hauing all rites and iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction which a Dioceſan, or prouinciall, or nationall church euer had or coulde haue. Alſo vnder the Goſpell, Saint
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10643:10"/> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> by warrant from the holy Ghoſt, appointed <hi>Timothy</hi> a prouinciall Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> hauing many Biſhops vnder him, and <hi>Titus</hi> a nationall Biſhop ouer all the kingdome of <hi>Crete,</hi> hauing many Churches and Biſhops vnder him, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5. . 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3 <hi>Eeſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> not onely the Scriptures, but alſo <hi>Euſebius,</hi> his wordes being theſe: <hi>Timotheus ſanè primus Epheſinae paraechiae, ſicut &amp; Titus Cretenſium Eccleſiarum Epiſcopatum ſortitus ſcribitur. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> was the firſt Biſhop of the whole praecinct of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in as ample manner as <hi>Titus</hi> of all the Churches of <hi>Creete.</hi> Thus haue I freed our Church Gouernment vnder Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan and Prouinciall Biſhops, from that ſlanderous imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of idolatry, ſeeing their inſtitution is of God, and no way oppoſite to his commandement.</p>
               <p>In his ſecond argument, he defineth that onely to be a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, which is indued with outward ſpirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. And ſo concludeth, that there can be no Dioceſan or Prouinciall, or Nationall Church, nor by a conſequent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch Biſhop, but onely pariſh Churches, and by the like conſequent, pariſh Biſhops. The reaſon of this ſequell, he produceth onely this: Becauſe, if there might be ſuch Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan, or Prouinciall, or Nationall Churches miniſteriall, or indued with Church gouernment, then alſo would it follow, that there might be a Catholike, or vniuerſall Church, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miniſteriall; and ſo by a conſequent, the Papiſts might lawfully inforce a Catholike gouernment, and ſo eſtabliſh the Papacie againe.</p>
               <p>To the ſequell of which ſequell I anſwer, it is no good conſequence, that; it being granted one may be a Biſhop o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer one Dioceſſe, Prouince, or Nation: therefore one may bee a Biſhoppe ouer the world. For firſt, one Biſhoppe cannot gouerne the whole worlde, conſiſting of manie Kingdomes, Oligarchies, and Democraticall ſtates, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſeuerall Princes, and temporall gouernours, as he can one Dioceſſe, Prouince, or Nation, ſubiect to one ſecular Prince. And ſecondly, we haue no example of any vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Biſhoppe that euer was ſince the beginning of the world, not the Pope himſelfe, which chalengeth that title,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10643:11"/> For the eaſt part of the world, which is the Greeke Church, was neuer yet ſubiect vnto him, neither could be induced to vſe the ſame rites, ceremonies, &amp; leitourgie which he vſeth. But of prouinciall and nationall Biſhops, wee haue exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples out of the Scriptures: the high Prieſtes among the Iewes were ſo ordained of God, &amp; that office not only cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, but alſo politicall; which office, ſo farre as it was po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall, might as well continew, and be executed in the ſame Temple by Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> the firſt Archbiſhop of Ieruſalem vnder the Goſpel, as it was by the high Prieſts vnder the Law, that which was ceremoniall being aboliſhed, euen as the obſeruation of the Sabaoth, beeing partly ceremoniall, &amp; partly morall, the ceremony being out of date, that which is morall, doth abide. Our Sauiour in the Goſpel reformed the Temple, but he did not plucke it downe, to ſhew that it <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 15.</note> might continue ſtill being lawfully vſed.</p>
               <p>Hauing anſwered his arguments, we will come to his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and bare coniectures, which without ſhew of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, he bringeth in defence of his aſſertion. Hee diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth Biſhops into ſixe ſorts, two lawfull, a pariſhionall Biſhop, or ordinary Paſtour, and a Dioceſan titular Biſhop, who hath a bare title aboue others, but no Epiſcopall iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction at all: theſe two ſortes it pleaſeth him to allow. A Dioceſan ruling Biſhop, which hath more power than Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of pariſh Churches, yet not ſole power to rule in his Dioceſſe, a Dioceſan Lord Biſhop' which ruleth by his ſole authoritie, a Patriarke, and a Pope; which foure ſorts he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth as repugnant to the lawes of the Scriptures. To ſpeake therefore of the firſt, which is but a Parſon of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; what example can he alledge to proue, that euer there was, or place of Scripture to proue that there ought to be ſuch a Biſhop? His bare opinion without proofe, can be no ſatisfaction to perſwade others, howſoeuer in his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, he may pleaſe himſelfe. He alledgeth, that all Biſhops mentioned in the new Teſtament, and in the Eccleſiaſticall writers which were within 200. yeares after our Sauiour Chriſt, were ſuch Biſhops. But that is his owne aſſertion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10643:11"/> without proofe, neither doth hee inſtance in any author which doth affirme the ſame. To diſproue him, beſides that, neither pariſh Churches, nor pariſhes were erected or inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted vntill 260. yeares after our Sauiour Chriſt, in the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Platina d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitis pontio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um. Charion Monarch.</hi> 4.</note> daies of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that they had their inſtitution not from God, but from the Pope, whereas wee haue examples of Dioceſan Churches out of Gods word, as before I haue proued: that all the Biſhoppes mentioned in Eccleſiaſticall writers, within 200. yeares after our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, were not pariſh Biſhops: wee haue for inſtance <hi>Iulian,</hi> the tenth Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 181. which was Biſhop of many Churches. For <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> writeth: <hi>Alexandrinarum Eccleſiarum Epiſcopatum accepit:</hi> he tooke vpon him the Biſhopricke of the Churches of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria.</hi> And againe, <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth of a Biſhop which was ſet ouer many Biſhops long before that time, in the daies of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, and by the appointment of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe. His words are theſe: <hi>Poſt, mortuo tyranno quùm</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eaſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>ex inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â Pathmo Epheſum reuerſus eſſet, abijt etiam rogatus ad vicina gentium loca, vt partim conſtitueret Epiſcopos, partim totas Eccleſias componeret, partim clerum ex his quos ſpiritus ſanctus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſorte deligeret. Quùm ergò ad ciuitatem quandam haud procul diſſitam, cuiui etiam nomen nonnulli dicunt, veniſſet, verſo ad cum vultu qui ſupèr cunctos Epiſcopos erat conſtitutus, adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem corpore valido, facie eleganti, animo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> feruenti conspicatus, hunc, inquit, tibi ſummo ſtudio, teſtibus Chriſto &amp; Eccleſiâ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo.</hi> When the Tyran (meaning <hi>Domitian)</hi> was dead, hee returned out of <hi>Pathmos</hi> to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> at the requeſt of others, he viſited the places bordering there vpon, that he might or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Biſhops, conſtitute Churches, and elect clergy men by lots, whom the holy Gooſt had aſsigned. And comming to a Citie not farre of, which by many other writers is expreſſy named, hee caſt his eye vpon that Biſhop which was ſet ouer all the reſt, and committed to his tuition, a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man proper in body, and faire in face, youthfull in courage, ſaying: I doe earneſtly commend vnto you this young man, witneſſes Chriſt and his Church.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:10643:12"/>
               <p> Such pregnant examples, all making againſt him, and none for him, that ye may know what motiue hath induced him to write, that all Biſhoppes within 200. yeares menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>Euſebius,,</hi> were but pariſh Biſhops: ſurely he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe willingly to be deceiued by the fallacye, called, <hi>fallacia figurae dictionis.</hi> For, <hi>Euſebius</hi> (ſaith he) ſheweth that the Churches of moſt famous Cities, were but pariſhes onely, as the pariſh of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the pariſh of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 2. <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> &amp;c. But all the cunning reſteth in the proofe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to ſhew that <hi>Euſebius</hi> did call them pariſhes. <hi>Euſebius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed writeth, that <hi>Celedion</hi> and <hi>Agrippa</hi> were Biſhops in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinâ paraechia,</hi> and ſo that <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in <hi>paraechia Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Epiſcopatum tenuit.</hi> But can Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> be ſo ſimple, as to take that weake aduantage of the word, and ſo to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret that Latine word <hi>paraechia,</hi> pariſh in the Engliſh tongue? and to reſtraine that word in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> to as ſmall limits and confines as a pariſh is with vs, that all the Chriſtians in it might meete together in one place to heare Diuine ſeruice, as with vs for the moſt part they doe? though in ſome places they cannot doe ſo. Can hee thinke this a good argument, that the praecincts of their Biſhoprickes, were called by this generall name <hi>paraechiae,</hi> bounds, or borders, containing and including ſome ſet compaſſe of ground and place; and this generall name <hi>paraechia,</hi> may alſo include the ſmall circuit of a pariſh, as well as a larger iuriſdiction: therefore they were but pariſh Biſhops? that the precincts of their Biſhoprickes were no larger then the praecincts of a pariſh, and that their Epiſcopall authoritie, was no more then the iuriſdiction of euery priuate Paſtour? In like ſort may I as well conclude, that <hi>paraechia</hi> doth alſo ſignifie a larger iuriſdiction, ſo as it haue confines, and a certaine limitation, as a Dioceſſe, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, a whole Kingdome: therefore that they were Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan, Prouinciall, and Nationall Biſhops. It is well knowne that <hi>Alexandria</hi> conteined many Churches, as appeareth by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> whom I haue alreadie cited, where he ſaith, that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the tenth, had <hi>Alexandrinarum Eccleſiarum Epiſcopatum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb lib.</hi> 5. <hi>hiſt. c.</hi> 9.</note> the Biſhopricke of the Churches of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And againe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10643:12"/> where we writeth: <hi>Primus poſt Marcum Apoſtolvm &amp; Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eeſeb. hiſt. l</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Anianus paraechiae Alexandrinae adminiſtrationem ſuſcepit: Anianus</hi> immediately ſucceeded <hi>Marke</hi> the Apoſtle and Euangeliſt, in the gouernment of the <hi>paraechia</hi> of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> That this <hi>parechia</hi> was ſuch a limitation as contained in it many Churches, it is manifeſt by the confeſsion of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> where he hath theſe words: that Saint <hi>Marke</hi> did <hi>primuus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias Alexandriae conſtituere:</hi> firſt inſtitute the Churches of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexandria.</hi> So then, if becauſe of the word <hi>paraechia, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſhould be held onely for a pariſh Biſhop, by the like abſurditie, Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> which was an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt, and did firſt conuert the Citizens of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and inſtituted many Churches there, ſhould not haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ouer his owne Churches, which his ſelfe inſtituted, but onely paſtorall authority ouer one of them, becauſe hee was <hi>Alexandrinae Eccleſiae adminiſtrator,</hi> gouernour of the Church of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth. And, that being an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, and of higher authority, which founded many chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſhould not be Biſhoppe ouer as many as <hi>Iulian</hi> his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, which was no Euangeliſt, nor founded none, and therefore was of leſſe dignitie and authority, becauſe the argument muſt follow, being deriued from the word in the ſingular number, hee did <hi>Alexandrinam Eccleſiam adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> gouerne the Church of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And, what is the true grammaticall ſignification of this Greeke word <hi>(paroicia)</hi> of whom <hi>paraechia,</hi> the Latine is deriued, no better witneſſe then <hi>Scapula</hi> himſelfe, which in his <hi>Lexicon</hi> writeth; That it ſignifieth any iuriſdiction which is limitted, or any Church, bee it great or ſmall, or manie Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. His wordes are theſe: <hi>(paroicia) incolam eſſe, item accolarum conuentus, &amp; accolatus, ſacraqúe vicinia, prò Eccleſiâ vſurpari dicitur Can:</hi> 18. <hi>Concilij Ancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rani.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, to ſpeake of the Biſhoppe without a Biſhopricke, whom hee calleth <hi>Titular Dioceſan,</hi> I would gladly haue for inſtance, when, and where there was anie ſuch Biſhoppe? For proofe thereof, hee alleageth nothing elſe, but his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10643:13"/> owne doubtfull coniecture, ſaying: <hi>Perhaps</hi> Iulian, <hi>the tenth Biſhop of</hi> Alexandria, <hi>was the firſt of that ſort.</hi> And againe: <hi>It ſeemeth to me that this was</hi> Ieroms <hi>meaning, that the firſt ruling Biſhop was</hi> Diony ſius, <hi>the thirteenth Biſhop of</hi> Alexandria. And againe, <hi>At</hi> Heracles <hi>it is probable there was a period of one ſort of Biſhops, and with</hi> Diony ſius <hi>began another. That priority of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of one Biſhop ouer a pariſh, ſeemeth to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued from</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus <hi>to</hi> Iulianus. And againe, <hi>Nothing letteth vs, but that we may thinke, &amp;c.</hi> To which I anſwer: his bare &amp; naked coniectures, and idle ſurmiſes, grounded vpon no reaſon nor authoritie, or proofe, but onely vpon: <hi>perhaps, it ſeemeth, it is probable, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing letteth but that we may thinke,</hi> are no warrant to the ſtate to diſturbe the peace, and diſcipline of our Church ſo long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, and to ouerthrow the gouernment of Biſhops, which hath continued among vs ſince Chriſtian religion was firſt planted, and the land conuerted to the faith. And therefore to him may fitly be applied, the ſaying of St. <hi>Paul: They would be Doctours of the law, and vnderſtand not what they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeake, neither whereof they affirme.</hi> It is more ſafe to beleeue with the Church, that <hi>Iulian</hi> the 10. was not the firſt Biſhop which had many Churches vnder him in title and name, but that all his nine predeceſſours, <hi>Marcus, Anianus, Albia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Cerdon, Pius, lustus,</hi> and the reſt, had the ſame prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence which hee had, and eſpecially Saint <hi>Marke</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Euangeliſt, and the firſt conuerter of that people, and founder of thoſe Churches. And that in other places, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes were ſet ouer many Churches before his time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue inſtanced out of <hi>Euſebius</hi> alreadie in a Biſhop in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> daies, which was <hi>ſuprà cunctes Epiſcopos conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> ſet ouer all the Biſhops in that place. And it is far ſafer to beleeue the wordes of <hi>Euſebius: Alexandrinarum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum Epiſcopatum accepit, &amp; ſuprà omnes Epiſcopos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutus est,</hi> hee was Biſhoppe of the Churches of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and, hee was ſet ouer all the Biſhoppes, to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of both title and iuriſdiction, according to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, vſe, and practiſe of all Churches, and not of bare title, without iuriſdiction, rather then to ſubſcribe to Maiſter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10643:13"/> 
                  <hi>Iacob,</hi> his opinion, which hath nothing to ground vpon, but his owne opinion, which hath no better proofe, then <hi>teste me ipſo,</hi> witneſſe my owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>And, not to paſſe ouer with ſilence thoſe foure ſorts of Biſhoppes whom hee condemneth as vnlawfull. <hi>Maiority,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of ruling Biſhoppes in the Dioceſſe, ſeemeth to haue begun with</hi> Dionyſius, <hi>the next ſucceſſour after</hi> Heraclas. To which I anſwere as before. <hi>Quaedam videntur &amp; non ſunt,</hi> many things ſeeme to be otherwiſe then they are: among which, this his ſuppoſition is one. Againe, <hi>Quoedam videntur pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioribus &amp; indoctioribus, quaedam pluribus &amp; ſan oribus,</hi> that may ſeeme ſo to the feweſt, and vnlearnedeſt, but to the moſt and ſoundeſt of iudgement, it ſeemeth otherwiſe, that this maiority of ruling in the Dioceſſe, began in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> not with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> which was the fourteenth, but with S. <hi>Marke</hi> which was the firſt Biſhop of that place; and with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in other places: and ſo continued by ſucceſſion from them, vntill theſe daies, vnleſſe when their ſucceſsion was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by warres, or ſchiſme, or perſecution.</p>
               <p>But to come to a Dioceſan Lord Biſhop, ruling by his ſole power, which is indeed, the chiefe matter now in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Such a Biſhop,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſeemeth not to haue beene establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in</hi> Ambroſe, Ierom, <hi>and</hi> Auguſtines <hi>time.</hi> It may be it ſeemeth not ſo to Maiſter <hi>Iacob;</hi> but it ſeemed ſo to <hi>Zozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene,</hi> that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> himſelfe did rule like a Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 24.</note> by his ſole authority, when meeting the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> as hee went to Church, without any conſent or conſultation had with other Prieſts, on a ſuddaine took him by the gowne in the ſight of the people, interdicted him both from the holy communion &amp; the Church, for the offence he had committed; and the Emperour obeyed his authority. His wordes are theſe: <hi>Imperator quum Mediolanum veniſſet, ad Eccleſiam proceſſit vt oraret. Sed quùm ad oſtium iam perneniſſet, occurrit et</hi> Ambroſius <hi>eius ciuitatis Epiſcopus: &amp; apprehenſâ illius purpû-â in prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entiâ populi, ſiſte gradum inquit, homini enim ob peccata prophano, &amp; manus innoxio ſanguine comaculatas habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non eſt antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poenitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> egerit, vel ſacrum ingredi ſolium</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:10643:14"/> 
                  <hi>vel ad diuinoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myſteriorum communionem admitti. Imperator li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem ſacerdotis admiratu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, cogitationibus conſcientiam accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantibus, regreſſus eſt poenitentia compunctus.</hi> The Emperour, when he came to <hi>Millanie,</hi> went towards the church to pray, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was but at the doore: <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the Biſhop of that citie, ran to him, caught him by his purple robe in the preſence of the people, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him to ſtay there, ſhewing that it was not permitted him, hauing defiled his hands with innocent blood, to goe into the Church, nor to be partaker of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, before he had ſhewed himſelfe penitent. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour meruailed at the great ſpirit of the Biſhop, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pricked him, vpon his remorſe, hee went backe and repented. And afterward, more plainly he ſaith: <hi>Ambroſius Imperatorem inſimulans, vt conſentaneum eſt, ab Eccleſiâ arcuit, &amp; à communione ſecluſit. Ambroſe</hi> laying to the Emperour his charge his crime which he committed, as it did behooue him, thruſt him out of the Church, &amp; ſecluded him from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. In this Story, that action is aſcribed ſolely vnto the Biſhop: no mention is made of any other, whoſe conſent was required. <hi>Though ſoone after we doubt not</hi> (ſaith Maiſter <hi>Iacob) it tooke place in the Church.</hi> Therefore, by his owne confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the office of Lord Biſhop, ruling by his ſole authoritie, is of great antiquitie: and therefore to be preferred before the Elderſhip, which is but a nouelty, and neuer preuailed vntill our age, and that but in ſome few Churches.</p>
               <p>And that I may ſpeake ſomething for the iuſtification of Biſhoppes, ruling by their ſole authority, <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were ſuch Biſhops. Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> replieth two manner of waies. Firſt he ſaith: the Apoſtles did not ordeine Miniſters, nor cenſure offenders by their ſole authority, much leſſe then <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> which were inferiour to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. For anſwer to his reply, which conſiſteth of nothing but manifeſt vntruthes, I do inſtance in S. <hi>Peter,</hi> which by his ſole authority, cenſured <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Suphira,</hi> when they lied to the holy Ghoſt, ſmiting them with preſent death: &amp; St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which alone cenſured <hi>Elymas</hi> the ſorcerer, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſmote him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 11</note> with blindnes, for ſeeking to peruert the deputy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10643:14"/> And both theſe cenſures were then in the place of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerum dè clauibus.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22. <hi>anathema maran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natha. Politiae Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicae. c.</hi> 2.</note> which is now the ordinarie cenſure of the church. And beſides that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> by his ſole authoritie excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in general, all that loued not the Lord Ieſus; euen vnder the time of nature, Henoch as <hi>Cornelius Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ram</hi> writeth in his booke Printed at <hi>Geneua,</hi> and allowed of by that church did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: <hi>anathema illud ſolenne ſuoe aetatis hominibus proponere quod extat Iudae ver:</hi> 14 <hi>&amp;.</hi> 15. pronounce that ſolemne ſentence of excommunication againſt the men of his time, of which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made in S. <hi>Iude</hi> ver. 14. &amp; 15. <hi>Behold the Lord commeth with thouſands of his Saints to giue iudgement, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo did Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> by their examples. And as for making Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, our Biſhops doe not conferre orders alone, but aſſiſted with other miniſters which ioyne with them in prayer &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands. Yet ſtill the chiefeſt authoritie reſteth in Biſhops, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> writeth to <hi>Titus: For this cauſe I left thee in Creete, that thou ſhouldeſt ordaine Elders in euery citie.</hi> And to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit:</hi> 1 5.</note> 
                  <hi>lay hands ſodainly on no man:</hi> by which words it appeareth that ordination, &amp; impoſition of hands belong to the Biſhops <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tit:</hi> 5. 22.</note> principally, and to the inferiour Miniſters but as aſſiſtants to the Biſhop. But that it belonged to the ſame men to cenſure offenders, &amp; rule by their ſole authoritie, the places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doe make it ſo plaine, that ir may not be denied. <hi>Rebuke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 1. 9. 11. 17. 19. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>not an Elder, but exhort him as a Father. Let not a widdow be taken into the number vnder</hi> 60 <hi>yeares old. Refuſe the yonger widdowes. The elders that rule wel, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be had in doble honor, Obſerue theſe things without preferring one before another, &amp; doe nothing parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Receiue no accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt an elder, but vnder</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>witneſſes.</hi> Secondly, he ſaith: that if theſe things were granted, that <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus</hi> ruled by their ſole anthoritie, it would not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that therefore our Biſhops might do the like: his reaſon is this: <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they are not to be reckoned in the catalogue of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; neither were they properly called Biſhops, becauſe they were not affixed to certaine places, but often remoued to other churches as the Apoſtles did.</hi> Which reaſon I refute by manifeſt text, for as much as <hi>Timothy</hi> was affixed to <hi>Epheſus</hi> as his proper charge, and ſo <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>Creete</hi> as to his peculiar place, witneſſeth the Apoſtle.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:10643:15"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>I beſougbt thee to abide ſtill in Epheſus. For this cauſe haue I left</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>thee in Creete that thou ſhouldeſt continue there to redreſſe the things that remaine</hi> But what then, though they afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and were called to other places? ſo are our Biſhops alſo, and priuate paſtours, oftentimes called from one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to another. I cannot deny, but the cannon Lawe hath determined, that Biſhops ſhal not remoue from one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke to another, without ſome vrgent cauſe, as when they are required by another Church, their gifts beeing thought fitter for a greater charge, and the lawe is grounded vpon the decrees of the firſt generall councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> which ſo concludeth: <hi>Epiſcopus, Presbyter, aut diaconus, non aebet tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri ab vnâ ciuitate ad a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam, quia id est contrà regulas, &amp; ſi tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feratur,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concilij Niceni:</hi> 1. <hi>Can:</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>mitti debet ad ciuitatem vbi primò ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us fuit.</hi> It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Canons, that Biſhops, Prieſts, Deacons, ſhould bee tranſlated, and therefore, if any be ſo tranſlated, let them be diſmiſſed, and ſent backe to the places to which they were firſt appointed. And, <hi>Qui diſcedit ab Eccleſiâ fibi commiſſa, ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, excommunicetur, &amp; reuerti cogatur.</hi> Who ſo remoueth from one Church to another, let him be excommunicated, &amp; forced to his firſt charge. But theſe are the ordinances of men, we find nothing in the word of God, why Biſhops may not be tranſlated, neither doth it followe that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were not to be reckoned for Biſhops, becauſe they remoued from one place to another.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, Patriarchical Churches (ſaith he) beganne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before the councell of <hi>Nice.</hi> I anſwer, therefore they are of more credit then the Presbyterie, which beganne but with Maiſter <hi>Caluin.</hi> And as for that Councell, it was in the pure age of the primitiue Church, before corruption crept in, it was the firſt general councell, and therefore of greater autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, called by the Emperour and not by the Pope, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore freeſt from ſuſpition, a <hi>Greeke,</hi> and not a <hi>Latine</hi> Councel, therefore more ſincere. And whereas it ſeemeth to him, that patriarchical Biſhops began but ſometime before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Nice,</hi> it ſeemeth to the Councel it ſelfe, that they began long before, becauſe the Canon it ſelfe ſpeaketh in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10643:15"/> 
                  <hi>Seruetur antiqua conſuetudo, vt Epiſcopus Alexandrinus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat potestatem in Aegyptum, Pentapolin, Libiam, quià &amp; Epiſcopo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil: Nicen</hi> 1. <hi>Can.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Romano parilis mos est, ſie apud Antiochiam, &amp; ceteras Eccleſias ſua priuilegia ſeruentur.</hi> Let the ancient cuſtome be kept, that the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> haue his iuriſdiction ouer <hi>Aegypt, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapolis</hi> and <hi>Libia,</hi> becauſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the like cuſtome, ſo let the Church of <hi>Antiochia</hi> and other Churches keepe their priuiledges. But if patriarchicall churches be of ſuch reuerend antiquitie, and allowed of by ſo venerable a councell: that maketh much for the credite, and dignitie of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan churches, which are more ancient and of leſſe iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not ſo ſubiect to enuie, and nere vnto Papacie, as the Patriarchicall churches are. It cannot be denied, but the Fathers which were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that Councel, were prouincial, Dioceſan, and patriarchicall Biſhops, ruling by their ſole au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. And concerning the credit of that councell, with the other three following, which were oecumenicall, as that was; <hi>Gregory</hi> affirmeth that their doctrine and decrees were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the writings of the 4. Euangeliſts, and no way to be impeached. And Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> his owne Doctor, whom hee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grëg: li.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt</hi> 24. <hi>Pag.</hi> 31. <hi>Reſponſ: ad</hi> 4. <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piani ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi>
                  </note> calleth the reuerend Maiſter <hi>Whitaker,</hi> giueth as large a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of them, ſaying: <hi>Et nos illorum quatuor Conciliorum ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berimam fuiſſe authoritatem planiſſimè confitemur.</hi> Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> therefore, muſt either denie the authoritie of his own Doctor, and of this Councell, which no learned man will doe, or elſe ſubſcribe to the ſtate of Dioceſan Biſhops ruling by their ſole authoritie, which hitherto he hath impugned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Cathedrall Churches.</head>
               <p>IN defence of Cathedrall Churches, wee haue to alledge, <note place="margin">Platima dè vitis Pontificu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Carion in ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: monar.</note> that till the time of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> no other kinde of Church miniſteriall was euer heard of from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. For, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> there was no Church miniſteriall at all. In <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, a Tabernacle was erected by Gods commandement, which ſtood in ſteede
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10643:16"/> of a Church for all the land of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> and was to be caried vp and downe, vntill the dayes of <hi>Solomon.</hi> But <hi>Solomon</hi> erected <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exed:</hi> 25. 40. <hi>Act:</hi> 7. 44 2. <hi>Sam:</hi> 7. 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 7, 47.</note> a Temple as a ſtanding church at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to be in the place of the Tabernacle. And vntill the time of the Goſpell there was no other Church for Gods people through the whole world. And that Church was more then Dioceſan, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall, for it was Nationall. After the Goſpell was preached to the Gentiles, &amp; al nations were conuerted, ſundry churches miniſteriall were erected, according to the number of the Biſhops, ſo that euery Biſhop had his Church after the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iewes, which hauing but one Biſhoprik, had alſo but one Church for that whole nation, vntill afterward hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane politie vnder <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Pope deuiſed pariſh chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and diuided euery Biſhoprik into particular conſtant congregations, which were but members of the Dioceſan and prouinciall Churches. But ſaith Maiſter <hi>Iacob, Although the Iewiſh Church were nationall vnder one Biſhop or high Priest according to Gods ordinance, yet now vnder the Goſpell, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt hath changed that forme of gouernment into parochiall Churches, which are euery one a particular congregation, and euery particular congregation is a diuided body by it ſelfe, and of it ſelfe a viſible Church, and being abſolute of it ſelfe, ought to vſe within it ſelfe proper Eccleſiaſticall gouernment.</hi> So then two things reſt to be proued by him, firſt that euery particular congregation is a diuided body of it ſelfe, and ſecondly, that euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar congregation is to vſe gouernment of it ſelfe without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference vnto any other aboue it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The firſt hee would proue by this argument. There was, ſaith he, but one Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>When the whole church is come together in one place, &amp;c.</hi> And the ſame may be affirmed of <hi>Rome, Antioch, Ieruſalem,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 23.</note> cities, therefore in euery of theſe cities, though they were ſo populous, yet the beleeuers were ſo fewe, that they all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in one place. Againe ſaith he, <hi>Ignatius</hi> perſwading the Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> to concorde, writeth: <hi>I exhort you to vſe one faith, one preaching, one ſupper of the Lord, for there is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ignatius ad philad:</note> 
                  <hi>but</hi> (en thuſiaſterion paſe te eccleſia) <hi>one communion Table to</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:10643:16"/> 
                  <hi>the whole church (HERE IN THIS CITIE).</hi> For an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer whereof I deny his argument, for a man may in the like manner write to the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> dwelling in <hi>Bowe</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, <hi>when your whole Church is come together:</hi> and ſo to them which dwell in any other pariſh, though there be many other Churches in <hi>London,</hi> and they not diuided bodies abſolute of themſelues, but all ſubordinate vnto, and members of that Church which belongeth to the whole Dioceſe. And ſo I anſwer to <hi>Ignatius</hi> his wordes: euery one of them haue one communion Table, not euery one collectiue, but diſtributiue, not iointly, but ſeuerally. But whervnto <hi>Ignatius;</hi> his words, he addeth his owne words <hi>(HERE IN THIS CITIE)</hi> he dealeth not ingenuouſly. For theſe words which he alledgeth out of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> as he alledgeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do not import that <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> whole citie ſhould haue but one Communion Table, and by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent but one church, but that the citie might haue many churches, and euery church his proper Communion Table, <hi>as with vs in this Citie.</hi> And againe, that there were many chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in thoſe cities which he named, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Apoſtles time, I haue alreadie proued, when I ſhewed out of <hi>Euſebius</hi> that not onely <hi>Iulian</hi> the 10. did <hi>Alexandrinarum, Eccleſiarum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatum accipere,</hi> take vpon him the gouernment of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb: hiſt: l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> churches of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> but alſo that Saint <hi>Marke</hi> did, <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imus Eccleſias Alexandriae conſtituere,</hi> firſt inſtitute many churches in <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And that the beleeuers were not ſo fewe, as that they might be aſſembled in one congregation, it is euident by the ſtorie of the Acts of the Apoſtles, and becauſe he nameth <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> I will inſtance in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> It is written in the Acts, there were men at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that feared God, of euery nation <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 5.</note> vnder heauen, which heard the Goſpell preached in their owne language<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and concerning the multitude of theſe ſaith Maiſter <hi>Beza,</hi> they are to be vnderſtood: <hi>Quicunqù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eri illo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Beza in annotat: mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rib in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilum locum.</note> 
                  <hi>tempore Hieroſolymis vrſabantur: adeò vt non modo exteros com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendat, quiſedes illic vt in vrbe maximâ, &amp; frequentiſſimâ poſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, ſed eos quoqùe qui ſtudiorum, &amp; religionis diſcendae canſâ illic ad tempus commorabantur, quorum diſtributa fuiſſe collegia intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus ex ijs quae narrantur</hi> Cap, 6. verſe 9. and 9. 29. <hi>All ſtrangers which at that time were reſiant at</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>that</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:10643:17"/> 
                  <hi>ſuch a multitude comprehendeth not onely the ſtrangers which had dwellings there, being ſo great and populous a citie, but alſo thoſe which were ſtudents, and came thither as vniuerſitie men for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſake, which were diuided into Colledges as appeareth by the Act. Ch:</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Where there aroſe certaine of the Synagogue which are called</hi> Libertines, <hi>&amp;</hi> Cyrenians, <hi>and of</hi> Alexandria, <hi>and of them of</hi> Silicia, <hi>&amp;</hi> Aſia, <hi>which diſputed with</hi> Stephen, <hi>and Act ch:</hi> 9. 29 <hi>where the</hi> Grecians <hi>diſputed with</hi> Paule. And againe (ſaith he) <hi>Oportuit tam amplam ciuitatem ad quam etiam vndiqùe Iudaei tanqum ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munem Academiam ſuos erudiendes mittebant, in varios cae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us diſtribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, quos apparet ex hoc loco pro nationum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietate fuiſſe diſtinctos, vt hedie Lutetiae multa collegia, &amp;c. So ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a citie to whom the Iewes farre and wide ſent their ſonnes as to a common vniuerſitie to be trained vp, was of neceſſitie diuided into many Colledges, as it is now at</hi> Paris, <hi>according the diuerſitie of the nations as out of this place it appeareth &amp;c.</hi> Againe, how did they all heare the Goſpel preached in their owne languages? <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Apoſtolus varij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> linguis loqui coepiſſe, id eſt modò hác modò iliâ, non tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſè aut furioſê, ſed prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c vel ille in varias gentes incide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, The Apoſtle ſheweth that they ſpake diuerſe languages, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly like mad men, but as this or that Apoſtle did happen vpon this or that nation ſo he ſpake to them in their owne language.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, at the very firſt there were diuerſe Preachers, and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall congregations, ſpeaking ſeuerall languages, vncapable of hearing the word preached before them al at one time, as they which be but one church or congregation. And againe, in the ſame chap: v 41. there were added to the church in one day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3000. &amp; ver. 47. the Lord added to the church from day to day. Yet Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> would haue all theſe, being ſo many thouſands, &amp; ſo many nations, not of one language, but ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diuerſe languages, to haue bin but one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they firſt all one congregation, &amp; then by reaſon of their great increaſe, as not able to aſſemble in one place, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided themſelues into many congregations, vpon the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Iacob</hi> affirmeth, but they were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny churches at the firſt, as I haue already proued, being ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nations, and ſpeaking ſeuerall languages, and thoſe many <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 1.</note> churches were ſcattered as it is written: <hi>A great perſecution was</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:10643:17"/> 
                  <hi>raiſed againſt the cburch of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they were ſcattered abroad through the regions of Iudaea &amp; Samaria.</hi> In which words the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt calleth <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> but one Church, which wee haue proued to haue conſiſted of diuerſe congregations, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all thoſe congregations were but one church, therefore they could not be diuided bodies abſolute of themſelues, &amp;c. And, wheras Mr. <hi>Iacob</hi> obiecteth that theſe congregations ſo diuided, were not to be called churches, becauſe they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, and but occaſionall. I anſwer, that ſo were all other churches in time of perſecution, euen thoſe churches which he mentioneth out of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> for as much as al the time of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> there was perſecution, &amp; long after his time, &amp; therefore they were but occaſionall, &amp; vncertaine. But this diſproueth me not, but that I do rightly alledge againſt him, that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers in <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> were more then could be aſſembled in one congregation, &amp; ſo in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and other cities. Secondly, he goeth about to proue that euery congregation is a diuided body abſolute in it ſelfe, becauſe the Scriptures ſtill ſpeake of the churches as of one. <hi>There is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4, 4. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>faith, one baptiſme, &amp;c.</hi> To which I anſwer, that theſe words are vnderſtood of Chriſt his vniuerſal church, which is <hi>inded vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſponſa, vnica columba,</hi> one Doue, one ſpouſe, betroathed to one husband, one body knit and vnited to one head, which is Ieſus Chriſt, for one head cannot haue many diuided bodies. And therfore this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maketh againſt himſelfe. The whole church is but one, &amp; therefore pariſh churches are but members of that one, and not diuided bodies, for <hi>vnitas non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt diuidi,</hi> that which is but one cannot be diuided.</p>
               <p>And that euery pariſh, or particular congregation muſt vſe gouernment within it ſelfe; he taketh vpon him to proue by the wordes of our Sauiour: <hi>If thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thee,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>goe tell him his fault betweene thee &amp; him alone if he heare thee, thou haſt won thy brother, if he heare thee not, take with thee one or two, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes euery thing may be confirmed, if he refuſe to heare them, tell it vnto the church, if he refuſe to heare the church, let him be to thee as a heathen and a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</hi> Out of theſe words (ſaith he) is proued that euery ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary congregation is a proper viſible Church, and a viſible
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10643:18"/> Church is but one congregation, and euery ſuch Church is indued immediately from Chriſt with power abſolute to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne within it ſelfe, and euery member of the Church muſt haue a ſenſible and viſible vſe of the whole intirely together. In which wordes he aſcribeth the Eccleſiaſticall gouernment to the whole multitude of euery pariſh. Further, he diuideth this Church gouernment into theſe two parts, to wit, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication and elections, ſo that euery priuate man (be hee neuer ſo vnfit) ſhould haue his free voice and conſent in all excommunications and elections. Eor anſwer whereof, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie his argument. For, beſides that, in the fift page of his booke, hee affirmeth that man cannot make a ſocietie to be a viſible church, but Chriſt alone, and it is proued that all theſe pariſhes are the inſtitution of men, which onely haue diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed the bounds of Pariſhes, and that very vnequally, making ſome too large, and ſome too ſmall, and ſo he contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteth himſelfe: the multitude haue not the keyes of the Church committed vnto them, but onely the miniſters, where our Sauiour ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> in the behalfe of the reſt: <hi>Tibi dabo claues,</hi> to thee I will giue the keyes. And to the Apoſtles, whoſe ſinnes yee remit, they are remitted: and whoſe ſinnes ye retaine, they are retained. And whereas there be two keyes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat:</hi> 16. 19. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. 23.</note> of the Church, the one of the word and the Sacraments, the other of gouernment: the key of gouernment witnes Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe, is not giuen to all miniſters, much leſſe to the people, but onely vnto ſuch miniſters as be magiſtrates of the Church, as <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> was. For ſaith he: <hi>Eccleſia inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum prò Senatu Eccleſiastico vſurpatur vt infrà</hi> Cap: Mat: 18. verſe 17. <hi>Dic Eccleſiae. This word Church, is ſometimes taken for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza in annotat: maior: in Mat:</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſenate or Conſiſtorie Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> as Mat: 18. 17. where our Sauiour ſaith: <hi>Tell the Church.</hi> And his owne Doctor Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> vpon this place expoundeth theſe wordes: <hi>Tell the church,</hi> more at large in his notes vpon that place, ſhewing that Maiſter <hi>Iacobs</hi> expoſition is very abſurde, and that ſuch diſcipline as that the peoples conſent ſhould bee required in excommunications, is very far from the diſcipline receiued in <hi>Geneua.</hi> His wordes are theſe. <hi>Dic Eccleſiae, ſpectat ad forum</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:10643:18"/> 
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quia verſu proximo fit mentio ligandi &amp; ſoluendi Haec potestas erat penes eos qui</hi> (archiſunagogo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>vocantur Marci</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Et huius conſcietudinis exemplum extat.</hi> Iohn 9. 22. &amp; 12. 42. &amp; 16. 2. <hi>Vt apud Iudaeos idem fuiſſe videatur paenaegenus</hi> (apoſunagogon geneſthai) <hi>at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> apud Chriſtianos excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari. Sed notandum est turpiter errare qui ex hoc confici volunt, dè ſingulis rebus referendum eſſe ad totius multitudinis caetum A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt enim Eccleſiae nomen nuſquam aliter accipi quod vel ex hoc ipſo loco falſum eſſe counincitur. Nam certè, tanquàm aè Iodaeis haec dici ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret, ſaitem ex eò quod addit: ſit tibi ficut Ethnicus &amp; publicamus. Sed iudicia de his rebus penes ſeniores fuiſſe apud Iudaeos, nec ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cogi conſueuiſſe totum populi caetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, omnes illaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum ſcriptores teſtantur Et certè Chriſtus niſi ad ſuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudinem totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hunc ſermone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modaſſet, quis eum loqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intellexiſſet? Quod ſi quis excipiat tyrannica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuiſſe illa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne id quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vere dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit quum Chriſtus ſic loqui non potuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, quin eum more<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt legitimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> approbaret. Theſe words: te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Church, belong to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal court, becauſe in the</hi> 9 <hi>verſe, mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made of binding &amp; loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. For this power belonged only vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which Mark</hi> 5. 22. <hi>were called the Rulers of the Synagogs. And we haue example of this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</hi> Iohn. 9. 22. <hi>where the Iewes had ordeined, that euery one which confeſſed Christ ſhould be excommunicated out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. And</hi> Iohn 12. 42. <hi>Among the chiefe Rulers, many beleeued in him, but becauſe of the Phariſies, they durst not cofeſſe him, lest they ſhould be caſt out of the Synagogue: and</hi> Ioh. 16. 12. <hi>They ſhall excommunicate you, and caſt you out of their Synagogues. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iews, to be caſt cut of the Synagogue, was all one, as among the Chriſtians to be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated. And, it is to be noted, that they erre filthity, which out of this place conclude: that in all matters of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, the multitude muſt be conſulted. And where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they obiect, that the name of the church is no where vnderſtord otherwiſe then for the multitude, their expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is out of this place conuicted to be falſe &amp; erroneous. For our Sauiour deliuereth theſe laws of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline to Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in the ſame maner as if he ſpake to the Iewes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaith: let him be to thee as an heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a Publica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But only the Magiſtrates amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Iews, did exerciſe theſe iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nts without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent &amp; knowledge of the people, as all their writers do teſtifie.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:10643:19"/> 
                  <hi>And ſurely, vnleſſe our Sauiour had applied his ſpeech vnto the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of his times, no man could haue vnderſtood what he meant by theſe words. And, if any ſhall obiect, that this cuſtome was tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and vnlawfull, hee deliuereth an vntruth in ſo ſaying: becauſe our Sauiour could not haue ſpoken to chriſtians after this maner of the Iewes, vnleſſe he had approued this maner of excommunication among the Iewes, which was by the Magiſtrates, and not by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to haue beene alſo lawfull, and to be vſed among chriſtians.</hi> So farre <hi>Theodorus Beza</hi> vpon this place.</p>
               <p>And, as for popular election, which is the other part of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment Eccleſiaſticall, to which hee intituleth the whole multitude: let the caſe be put, that ſometimes of fact, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had a conſent in the election of their Biſhops, in time of perſecution: and, when the church being not indowed with any landes or maintenance, they liued onely by charity and deuotion of the people: what proofe hath he that it ought to be ſo? or that euer it was ſo in any ſetled eſtate? Hee ſaith it is plaine, the people had their free election of their Biſhops in the daies of <hi>Ignatius;</hi> becauſe in one epiſtle hee writeth theſe words: <hi>Prepon eſi vmin es eccleſia theou cheirotoneſai ton epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copon vmon;</hi> which ignorantly he engliſheth in this maner: It is meete for you, being the church of God, to chooſe by common conſent your Biſhop. Firſt, it is well knowne, that when <hi>Ignatius</hi> liued, which was in the very infancy of the Church, there was neither any certaine maintenance for the Miniſters, nor any ſetled eſtate of a Church, but all liued vpon the beneuolence of the people. Secondly, this word Church, ſignifieth not the people, but the Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as before I haue ſhewed you out of Mr. <hi>Beza.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no learned man would haue tranſlated this word <hi>(cheiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toneo)</hi> to chooſe by common conſent, as he hath tranſlated it. For, the very grammaticall ſignification of this word is, not to elect by ſuffrages, or voyces, or lifting vp of hands, as the people chooſe their Mairos, or Bailiffes, and ciuill officers; but conſecration by impoſition of hands, as all Miniſters are to be conſecrated, by the rule of the Scriptures. That the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould haue any voyce in elections; it is ſo ſtrange a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10643:19"/> as was neuer read of in the Scriptures. For, as no man <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>Exod</hi> 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note> may enter into the miniſterie without a lawfull calling, (for our Sauiour had his calling from his Father, <hi>Moſes</hi> from God, <hi>Aaron</hi> from <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Apoſtles from our Sauiour, <hi>Timothy</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus,</hi> from S. <hi>Paul)</hi> ſo we muſt conſider in whom this authority reſteth, to call men to the miniſtery: for none of theſe of whom I haue ſpoken, had any conſent of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This cuſtome of popular election is borrowed out of the Turkes Alcaron, and not of the Bible. It is ſaide to the congregation, concerning the election of Deacons; <hi>Looke ye out</hi> 7. <hi>men of honeſt conuerſation, &amp;c:</hi> by which it is iuſtified which our law doth require, that they vpon whom the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6.</note> ſhall lay hands, muſt bring with them ſufficient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their worthineſſe: but in the words following it is ſaid; <hi>whom we may appoint to this buſineſſe.</hi> And afterward, verſe 6. when they were found out, they ſet them before the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the Apoſtles prayed, and laide hands vpon them, but not the people, as our Biſhops aſſiſted with other mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, without the helpe of the people, ordeine miniſters with vs. Therefore in their obiection out of the Acts, where they alleage theſe Engliſh words; <hi>When they had ordeined Elders by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>election, in euery Church, &amp;c:</hi> they doe but deceiue themſelues. For the Greeke word is <hi>(cheirotoneo)</hi> of <hi>(cheir)</hi> an hand, and <hi>(teino) porrigo, extendo, noteleno,</hi> to reach, or ſtretch forth, or lay on, not to eleuate or lift vp; ſo <hi>(cheirotoneia)</hi> is not eleuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but impoſition of hands, in Ecceſiaſticall writers. Theſe words then: <hi>(cheirotoneſantes eautois presbuterous)</hi> is, <hi>manuum impoſitione conſecrantes ſibi ipſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> presbyteros,</hi> when by impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands, they had conſecrated Elders, or Miniſters, as <hi>Moſes</hi> by impoſition of hands, conferred the holy Ghoſt vpon <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and ſanctified him to be a Magiſtrate: and our <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.</note> Sauiour in the Goſpel, by laying hands on the children, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(cheirotoneia)</hi> is expreſſed more plainely by another Greeke word in the Acts of the Apoſtles, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6.</note> the conſecration of Deacons, to be <hi>(epitheſis ion cheiron)</hi> impoſition of hands, where the text ſaith: <hi>(proſeuxamenoi op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thecan autois tas cheiras)</hi> when they had prayed, they layed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10643:20"/> hands vpon them. And <hi>Gual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> in his Commentary vpon that place of the Acts, which before was alleaged, when they had ordeined Elders by election in euery Citie, after he hath iuſtified theſe popular elections vſed in the Church of <hi>Tigurie,</hi> and diſpraiſed our manner of ordination, reuoketh himſelfe, and confeſſeth by the word <hi>(cheirotoneſantes) magis veriſimiliter hîc incelligi manuum impoſitionem, &amp; non incerto po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo rem tam ſeriam committendam:</hi> that in that place, impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands is rather to be vnderſtoode, then any popular election, and that a matter of ſo great importance as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters, is not to be committed to the rude and inconſtant common people.</p>
               <p>He commeth now to his <hi>ob &amp; Sol:</hi> and obiecteth in our behalfe, as we doe our ſelues commonly alleage; that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with the ſtate of a Kingdome, that there ſhould be a popular gouernment of the Church. And he anſwereth himſelfe, that it is not requiſite that the gouernment of the Church ſhould bee anſwerable to the gouernement of the Realme. To which his anſwer I reply, that if the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church be not anſwerable to the gouernment of the Realme, then our aſſertion is true, that this popular gouernment cannot ſtand with the ſtate of a Kingdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King is by the people excluded out of the Church gouernment. With vs Biſhops are the Kings Lieutenants in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and all Eccleſiaſticall Courts are the Kings Courts, they be held immediately vnder the King, his authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, being ſubalternate, and immediately ſubordinate vnto our Sauiour Chriſt. Now for as much as they which hold with the lay Elderſhip, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular gouernment, doe claime their authority immediately from God, without the King, they derogate from the Kings authority in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and in Church matters they hold him for no King.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whereas we obiect, that popular gouernment with vs, cannot be but tumultuous: and hee anſwereth, that no tumults can ariſe by their gouernment, conſidering foure circumſtances. Firſt, that it is Gods ordinance. Secondly,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10643:20"/> that it is to be executed by no greater multitude then a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Thirdly, that the Church guides being ſeperated from the people, determine the matter and prepare it, onely the people conſent with them. Fourthly, if any few be violent and vnruly, the next Iuſtices are to keepe the peace among them. It is but an anſwerleſſe anſwer. For firſt, that popular gouernment is not Gods, but mans ordinance, as I haue ſhewed. Secondly, it is apparant, that diuers pariſhes with vs be ſo populous, that they conſiſt of many thouſands, and are as large in compaſſe, as ſome Dioceſſe in other places. Thirdly, for the guides of the Church, priuately to agree vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter, and to vrge the people, and conſtraine them by the authority of Iuſtices of peace, to yeelde vnto that which they haue decreed, is as much as to make it no popular election at all, becauſe then free conſents are denied them, and all authority reſteth in the guides of the Church. For, if there be no tumult, it is wholly in the power of the Church Magiſtrates, to conclude and eſtabliſh what they liſt, and the people muſt agree to it: if there be a tumult, the Magiſtrates of the Church are to command the Iuſtices to execute what their ſelues would haue done: ſo that the people are vſed but as ciphers, and haue no liberty in themſelues. So this is as good as no election.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Lord Biſhops, and Eccleſiasticall perſons, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing ciuill authoritie.</head>
               <p>THe common obiection is, that our Sauiour being the chiefe Biſhop, was not held for a Lord, neither had hee any outward pompe or glory in this world. To which I anſwer: if ſo be they inferre this concluſion vpon that example therefore, Biſhops muſt not be Lords: the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that argument will appeare by the like: for they may as well conclude againſt Kings; that becauſe our Sauiour being a King, yet was no Lord, had no pompe nor glorie-therefore
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10643:21"/> Kings muſt not be Lords, &amp;c. I could anſwer fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.</note> that he was a Lord, and ſo the Apoſtle doth call him a great Lord, and the head of the Church, and the Prince of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 15. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.</note> the kings of the earth: and becauſe he is head of the Church, all Kings doe holde their Crownes vnder him. That the world did not acknowledge him for a Lorde, it was their blindneſſe. Hee came to be crucified, and had the world knowne him, <hi>non Dominum gloriae crucifixiſſent,</hi> they had not crucified the Lord of glory. And yet in his ſtate of humility, hee had an honourable retinew to attend vpon him, to the number of eighty two, his twelue Apoſtles, and ſeuenty Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> was his treaſurer or pursbearer, he ſent <hi>Philip</hi> to the market to buy bread, he imployed his Diſciples in ſuch ſeruices as to him did appertaine, as appeareth by the ſtory of the Goſpel. But thus I prooue that Biſhops ought to be Lords: Our Sauiour being asked whether a man might put away his wife? anſwereth negatiuely, his argument of proofe being drawne from the law of nature, ſaying: <hi>Ab initio non fuit ſic,</hi> from the beginning it was not ſo. Likewiſe the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.</note> followeth: Biſhops ought to be Lords, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons to exerciſe ciuill authority, <hi>quoniam ab initio fuit ſic,</hi> becauſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning it was ſo. From <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> it was ſo, from <hi>Moſes</hi> to our Sauiour Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles it was ſo, with them it was ſo, and from them it hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo vntill this time, excepting onely the times of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the courſe of the Goſpel was interrupted, and there was no ſetled ſtate of a Church. No meruaile though in time of perſecution, they were not held for Lords, for then they were not allowed to be Citizens, nor thought worthy to liue in a Common wealth. The Pagan Emperours helde them for ſeditious perſons, troublers of the ſtate, and of all men moſt worthy of death. Our queſtion is not what then was of fact, but what ought to haue beene of right. It muſt not ſeeme ſtrange that Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> or Saint <hi>Paul</hi> could not be in authority vnder <hi>Nero</hi> &amp; <hi>Domitian,</hi> nor the godly Biſhops vnder the ten perſecutions, ſceing our Sauiour was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed any authority vnder <hi>Herod,</hi> nor <hi>Pilat,</hi> nor <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> nor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10643:21"/> 
                  <hi>Tiberius.</hi> No meruaile though <hi>Titus</hi> could not be held as a Lord in the Kingdome of <hi>Creete,</hi> ſeeing that neither <hi>Iehoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haz,</hi> being lawfully anoynted King of <hi>Iuda,</hi> could not reigne <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 25. 2. <hi>Rug.</hi> 24</note> as a King, being taken captiue by <hi>Pharao,</hi> nor <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> nor <hi>Sedechias,</hi> being oppreſſed by <hi>Nebuchadnezer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Adam</hi> vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> he that was the eldeſt of euery <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26 <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 23 <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 3. 4</note> familie, was both the king and the prieſt ouer his own fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, among Gods people. So <hi>Adam</hi> was a king, becauſe God gaue him abſolute power ouer the whole world: he was alſo a prieſt, for hee offered ſacrifice: <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> brought to him their ſacrifices, that he might offer in their behalfe, they are onely ſaide to haue offered, as <hi>Aſa</hi> the King, and all the people are ſaide to haue offered, when the Prieſt did offer in <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 15</note> their behalfe. <hi>Henoch</hi> ſeeing the children of God to fall dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from faith to infidelity, which was the cauſe of the deluge, publiſhed againſt them the ſentence of excommunication, ſaying: <hi>The Lord commeth,</hi> which is the moſt grieuous kinde of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> did borrow that form of him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudae. v.</hi> 14</note> where he writ; <hi>Hee that loueth not the Lord Ieſus, let him be an athema marannatha, curſed vntill the Lords comming.</hi> And <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16</note> did reckon vp ſo long a catalogue of all the eldeſt ſonnes deſcended from <hi>Adam</hi> before the flood, to this end, that it <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.</note> might appeare vnto whom from time to time the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the care of gouerning &amp; inſtructing the Church. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> a king, was a preacher of righteouſneſſe one hundred and twenty yeares before the flood, hee offered ſacrifice after the flood. That <hi>Iethro</hi> the father in law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was both a <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 20. <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 12. 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 16. 17.</note> prince &amp; a prieſt: &amp; likewiſe <hi>Iob,</hi> in the land of <hi>Huz,</hi> no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man will deny. And that none might offer ſacrifices, but the eldeſt and Princes of euery family, it appeareth by the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe God ſaid, he would <hi>take the tribe of Leui, to be ſeperated for his ſeruice, as a redemption of all the reſt of the first borne of Iſrael.</hi> In which words, hee did but call to remembrance the time of nature, wherein the eldeſt were all his: that is, they were conſecrated for the offering of ſacrifice vnto him. When <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was King and Prieſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge.</hi> 14. 18</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo was King and Prieſt ouer his own family.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10643:22"/> It was ſaide of him, <hi>Thou art a great Prince of God among vs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. 6 <hi>Ge.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Ge.</hi> 22. 10 <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Ge.</hi> 26. 24</note> And he taught them Gods word, he erected an altar, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſacrifice. To him firſt was committed the ſacrament of circumciſion, and he circumciſed his ſonne <hi>Iſaac. Iſaac</hi> his heire, crected an altar, and offered cacrifice for the exerciſe of his faith. <hi>Iacob</hi> after him did the like, taught purity of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and how Idolls were to be aboliſhed. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge.</hi> 35. 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the daies of <hi>Moſes,</hi> vnder the time of the law, when prieſthood was appropriated to one peculiar tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> and the Biſhoprick to one certaine family, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> both being prieſts, <hi>Moſes</hi> the yonger brother had the chiefe authority in ciuill buſineſſes, <hi>Aaron</hi> the elder in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cauſes: but all ſupreame authority was committed to theſe two prieſts, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> That <hi>Moſes</hi> was a prieſt, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. 6. 7. 8.</note> it is euident, becauſe all the whole tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> were then conſecrated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o holy prieſthood, whereof hee was one, hee in particular offered ſacrifice, preached Gods word, conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 40. <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> to be an high prieſt, and <hi>Eleazar</hi> in his place when he was dead, conſecrated the altar, which none could doe without ſacrilege but a prieſt. Yet he was the ſupreame ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil Magiſtrate. And in his abſence 40. daies he ſubſtituted <hi>Aaron</hi> the prieſt in his roome, to heare ciuill cauſes, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the place of a ciuill Magiſtrate. <hi>Phinees</hi> the high prieſt, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.</note> was a Captaine in warre, and buſied himſelfe with ſecular affaires, and it pleaſed God ſo much, that the prieſthood was conferred not onely vpon him, but alſo his poſterity. <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, who miniſtred before the Lord in a linnen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod,</hi> was alſo the chiefe ciuil Magiſtrate, and in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did ride his circuit as a Iudge euery yeare ouer all the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 12. 18. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.</note> land. All the daies of the Iudges, which was about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninety and nine yeares from the death of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> vnto <hi>Eli</hi> the prieſt, there was no certaine ſupreame ciuill magiſtracie in any, but in the high prieſts or Biſhops, among the people. When the people deſired a king of God, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulted with <hi>Samuel</hi> in that ſecular buſines. After thoſe 299. yeares of the Iudges, <hi>Eli</hi> the Biſhop reigned as ſupreame ciuill Magiſtrate 40. yeares: ſo did <hi>Samuel</hi> after him the ſpace of 40. yeares.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10643:22"/> Afterward, when <hi>Saule</hi> was by him annointed King, yet <hi>Samuel</hi> ruled ioyntly with <hi>Saule</hi> ſo long as he liued, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, bore the greateſt ſway in the realme, becauſe <hi>Saule</hi> had little more then the title of a King, during the life of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> and was to doe nothing without allowance from him.</p>
               <p>How the Clergie among Gods people buſied themſelues with the affaires of the temporal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, and howe much they pleaſed God in ſo doing, it appeareth by theſe examples. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 31 6. 26. <hi>Numb:</hi> 34. 17. <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 22. 13. <hi>Numb:</hi> 26. 63. 64. 2. <hi>Chron:</hi> 13. <hi>Ioſua,</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Pet:</hi> 23. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Phinees</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Biſhoppe, was a Captaine againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi> and <hi>Eleazar</hi> his ſelfe, ioyntly with <hi>Moſes</hi> diuided the ſpoyles among the Souldiers, <hi>Eleazar</hi> with <hi>Ioſua</hi> diuided the land of promiſe among the Tribes, <hi>Phineas</hi> the Biſhop was ſent Ambaſſador to proclaime warre againſt <hi>Gad, Ruben,</hi> and halfe <hi>Manaſſes, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Eleazar</hi> numbred the people in the plaine of <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in the wildernes of <hi>Sina.</hi> The Prieſts and Leuites ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their Trumpets, and bid the battell in the warre of <hi>Abias</hi> againſt <hi>Ieroboam.</hi> The Prieſts ouerthrewe the citie <hi>Iericho.</hi> And the godly King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſetting the Kingdome in better order then it was before, appointed 6000. Leuites to be Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Magiſtrates ouer the people. Likewiſe, beyond <hi>Iordan</hi> towardes the Weſt, 1700. both to ſerue God in the place of Leuites, and alſo to ſerue the King in ciuill offices pertaining to the common wealth, and alſo 2700. he ſet ouer <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to heare and determine all cauſes, both eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and ciuill, concerning God in the Church, and the King in the common wealth.</p>
               <p>The Kings were annointed, and confirmed in their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by the hands of the Biſhops, &amp; eccleſiaſticall perſons. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam:</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Sam:</hi> 16. 1. <hi>Reg:</hi> 1.</note> So <hi>Samuel</hi> annointed <hi>Saule</hi> &amp; <hi>Dauid, Sadoc</hi> annointed <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> when <hi>Adoniah</hi> had proclaimed himſelfe King, by help of <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt: <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet ſaid to <hi>Dauid:</hi> me thy ſeruant, &amp; <hi>Sadoc</hi> the Prieſt, haue they not called, nor <hi>Benoiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ichoiada.</hi> Then <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid: <hi>Call me</hi> Sadoch <hi>the Prieſt, and</hi> Nathan <hi>the Prophet and let them annoint and proclaime</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier:</hi> 26. <hi>Exod:</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>King.</hi> Ieremy <hi>was condemned to death by the Prieſts and the Prophets. The Leuites by the commandement of</hi> Moſes <hi>ſlewe with the ſword</hi> 3000. <hi>that committed idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:10643:23"/>
               <p> It was commanded by God, that when they went to warre, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex:</hi> 32. <hi>Deut:</hi> 20. <hi>Deut:</hi> 21. 19. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15</note> the Prieſts ſhould go before them &amp; exhort them to be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and valiant. That if there were inquiſition after mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Prieſts ſhould come forth, and by their word the cauſe ſhould be tryed. <hi>Samuel</hi> valiantly ſlewe <hi>Agag</hi> the King of the <hi>Amalakites,</hi> whom <hi>Saule</hi> the King for fooliſh pittie could not find in his heart to ſmite.</p>
               <p>Godly <hi>Ioſephat</hi> in his reformation of the Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron:</hi>
                  </note> wealth, appointed Iudges in euey citie throughout the land, as it appeareth, verſe 5. And what kinde of men theſe Iudges were, it appeareth in the 8. verſe following. In <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as alſo in other cities, he appointed Iuges out of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of euery family, and the Prieſts and Leuites which were to heare both ciuil and Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, (and ſo doth <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> expound it according to the truth of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> text) and at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> which was the chamber of the Kingdome, there was eſtabliſhed by him the higheſt bench of iuſtice, vnto which, as vnto the higheſt court, it was lawfull to appeale from all inferiour Courts and Iudges, euen as it is now with the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> and the high commiſſion Court at <hi>London.</hi> And among theſe Iudges who were to take place before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is explaned in the 11. verſe of that chapter, namely, in eccleſiaſticall cauſes, eccleſiaſticall men: in temporall cauſes, temporal men: but ſo that in euery ciuil court of Iuſtice there ſhould be ſome Prieſts and Leuites in Commiſsion.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the Lord ſaith: <hi>If there ariſe a matter too hard for thee in iudgement, betweene blood, and blood: plea, and plea: plague,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut:</hi> 17. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and plague: in the matters of controuerſie within thy gates, then ſhalt thou ariſe, and goe vnto the place which the Lord thy God ſhal chooſe, and thou ſhalt come to the Prieſts of the Leuites, and to the Iudge that ſhal be in thoſe dayes, and aske, and they ſhal ſhew thee the ſentence of iudgement; &amp; thou ſhalt doe according to the thing which they of that place (which the Lord hath choſen) ſhal ſhewe thee, &amp;c. and that man which wil doe preſumptuouſly, not hearkening to the Prieſt which ſtandeth before the Lord thy God to miniſter there, and the Iudge, that man ſhal dye, and thou ſhalt take eway euill from Iſrael, ſo all the people ſhal heare, and feare, and doe no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:10643:23"/>
               <p> As for <hi>Ezra</hi> the Prieſt, he had authoritie from <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to order all matters whatſoeuer, ſpiritual, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.</note> and temporall: concerning the returne of the people out of captiuitie, he ordered both the Princes and the people, Prieſts and Leuites, he appointed al the Iudges in the land, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer would not doe according to the Lawe of God, and the Kings Lawe, ſhould haue iudgement without delay, whether it were vnto death, or baniſhment, or confiſcation of goods, or impriſonment. And there was by <hi>Ezra</hi> ſet down the whole <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.</note> platforme of the ciuill eſtate of the common wealth. Againe, he gathered together the Princes, and all the Clergy, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a faſt, humbled them before God, that hee would guide them in their iourney, beeing aſhamed to aske of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> an Army of horſemen to helpe them, becauſe he had ſaide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that their truſt was in God alone. In the 10, Chapter hee cauſeth all, as well temporall as ſpirituall, to ſweare that they would put away their ſtrange wiues, cauſed a proclamation to goe out through <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to aſſemble in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> within three dayes in paine of confiſcation of their goods.</p>
               <p>How afterward the <hi>Maccabes,</hi> being Gods ſeruants, held both the Prieſthood and the Kingdome among the <hi>Iewes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods people, and that without impeachmenr, the learned know very well, and that they continued both high Prieſts and alſo Kings vntil the land was conquered by the Romans, and the ciuill gouernment committed vnto the family of the Herods, vntil the comming of our Sauiour Chriſt, who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated both the kingdome and the Prieſthood of right vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>And, whereas ſome men doe obiect againſt theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.</note> by me alledged for confirmation of ſpirituall mens au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in temporal cauſes among Gods people; That when our Sauiour Chriſt was to bee arrayned, they brought him from the high Prieſt, to the iudgement ſeate of <hi>Pilate</hi> a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Iudge, and ſaide to <hi>Pilate,</hi> verſe 31. <hi>It is not lawful for vs to put any man to death.</hi> I anſwere, firſt the Prieſt in particular did not ſay theſe wordes: <hi>It is not lawfull for vs to put any man to death,</hi> but the Iewes in generall, not to the preiudice of Prieſts
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10643:24"/> onely but of the whole nation of the Iewes. Secondly, they ſpeake not theſe wordes, as if the Iewes had of right from God no authoritie to put me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death. For <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf doth confeſſe, that they had right in themſelues, where he ſaith: <hi>Take him, and iudge him according to your owne lawe.</hi> But theſe wordes are to be vnderſtood, that according to the Lawes of <hi>Herod</hi> a ſtranger, and of the Romans which made them tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and by force tooke from them all power of life &amp; death, not onely from the Prieſts, but alſo from the whole nation, 40. yeares before that time, as Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> hath well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it was not lawfull for them to put any man to death. Thirdly, if the Iewes had had all their authoritie in their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza in annot: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorib: in Ioh:</hi> 18.</note> hands without controlment, yet it appeareth by the 28. verſe of that chapter, that the Prieſts at that time would not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at that iudgement where ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence of death was to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, becauſe the feaſt of <hi>Easter</hi> was at hand, and ſo doing they ſhould haue made themſelues vncleane, and by a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent diſinabled themſelues from executing their office at that ſolemnitie.</p>
               <p>Thus you haue heard proued out of the holy Scriptures, that among Gods people, in that kingdome which was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned according to Gods own lawes, euen then when it was reformed by godly kings, there was no bench of Iuſtice for hearing and ending of ciuill cauſes, vpon which Prieſts and Leuites did not ſit as Iudges and Iuſtices. Therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand other ſound reaſons, or places of Sctipture, to proue why it ſhould not ſo continue among vs which are alſo Gods people, eſpecially our Eccleſiaſticall perſons being more honourable vnder the Goſpel, then they were vnder the law? I confeſſe that the <hi>Popes</hi> lawes haue decreed the contrarie, but <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lancelelot iuſtitut: iuris can: l</hi> 1. <hi>Tit:</hi> 4. <hi>Concil: Lat:</hi> 31. <hi>partis</hi> 1. <hi>can:</hi> 12.</note> it is not fit that wee which are a reformed Church, and haue long ſince abandoned the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, ſhould nowe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God, and the examples of the holy Bible to followe the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Canons. The <hi>Popes</hi> lawe ſaith: <hi>Laici ſunt quibus licet temporalia prſſidere, vxere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ducere, cauſes agere, intèr virum &amp; virum iudicare, Clerici qui diuinis officijs mancipati ſunt, &amp; quos ab omni ſtrepitu ceſſare conueuit.</hi> Lay men are they to whom it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10643:24"/> is lawful to haue temporal poſſeſſions, to marie wiues, handle cauſes and controuerſies in Law, to iudge betweene man, and man: but as for Clergy men, their ſtate and condition is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they are ſo deuoted and mancipated to the ſeruice of God, that they muſt not intermeddle with ſuch worldly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Some of our brethren giue this anſwerles anſwer: that arguments drawen from the ſtate of the Miniſterie in the olde Teſtament, to that which is vnder the Goſpell, doe not holde, that we muſt not followe examples of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Church gouernment, and that therefore the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument doth not followe, that becauſe Biſhoppes in the olde Teſtament were Lords, and of the Kings Counſell in the higheſt place, and inferiour Miniſters were ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, therefore vnder the Goſpell it may be ſo, although what ſhould hinder, they cannot ſhewe. But that I may followe them in that courſe of diſputation: They ſay wee muſt not followe the examples of the olde Teſtament in Church gouernment, and that therefore the argument doth not followe: Biſhops in the olde Teſtament were Lords, and Kings Counſellers, and inferiour Miniſters were ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, therefore vnder the Goſpel they muſt be ſo. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I alledge, that by the like reaſon, theſe arguments which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Iuell,</hi> and the learned men of the reformed churches haue vrged againſt the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, and for the vpholding of Princes cannot follow, when they conclude in this manner: <hi>Solomon</hi> depoſed <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt for committing high Treaſon, and placed <hi>Sadoc</hi> in his roome, therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell Chriſtian Kings may puniſh their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for high Treaſon: <hi>Ezechias</hi> reformed the Church, <hi>Ioſias</hi> reade the Lawe before the Prieſtes in the houſe of the Lord, and commanded <hi>Helchias</hi> the high Prieſt, and the Prieſts of the ſecond order, to bring forth of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all the veſſells made for <hi>Baall,</hi> put downe Idolls, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg:</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Reg:</hi> 18.</note> ſlewe the idolatrous Prieſtes; therefore Chriſtian Kings may put downe idolatrie, and reforme the Church: You ſee thereforefore the weakenes, and great vnſufficiency of this anſwere.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:10643:25"/>
               <p> Againe, why doe the Lawes of <hi>Geneua</hi> puniſh adulterie with death after the example of the olde Teſtament, and why doe our brethren, which ſtand for the reformation, labour that the ſame puniſhment may bee inflicted vpon adulterers with vs, vrging vs with the authoritie of that Law, if ſo be that they will holde that the Lawes of the old Teſtament may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile vnder the Goſpell? In their ſimplicitie and want of iudgement, they ſhape this anſwere, as if it were the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to blowe downe <hi>Iericho, Dauids</hi> ſling to kill <hi>Golias, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> iawe-bone to ſlay a thouſand Philiſtines, that the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Lawe is aboliſhed, whereas before I haue ſhewed, thal this is not ceremoniall, but politicall, and that the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is aboliſhed, whereas onely that which is ceremonicall, concerning the Prieſts office is aboliſhed, but that which is moral indureth to the end. And againe, a Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell may with more conueniencie be a ciuill Magiſtrate, then the Prieſts vnder the Lawe, becauſe now the daily ſacrifices, the great number of feaſts, and ſolemnities, the infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ceremonies do ceaſe, which then procured vnto them a whole world of buſineſſes in their Miniſtery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by which they had leſſe vacant time to heare ciuill cauſes, then our Miniſters haue vnder the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwer to the common obiection, Luk:</hi> 22, 25. <hi>they that beare rule ouer them, are called gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lords, but ye ſhall not be ſo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the opening of this text, theſe things are to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Firſt, whether our Sauiour ſpake theſe wordes to his</p>
               <p>Apoſtles onely, or in the name of the Apoſtles to al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? For albeit the Apoſtles onely were perſonally preſent, and his apoſtrophe was vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet many circumſtances do proue that theſe words doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne al Chriſtians. For, firſt we find elſe where another ſpeech parallel vnto this: The Scribes and Phariſies loue the chiefe places at feaſts, and to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat:</hi> 2. 3.</note>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:10643:25"/> haue the chiefe ſeates in the aſſemblies, and greeting in the markets, and to be called of men: <hi>Rabbi, Rabbi:</hi> that is, Lord, Lord: but be not yee called <hi>Rabbi:</hi> for one is your <hi>Rabbi,</hi> to wit, Chriſt, and all ye are brethren, &amp;c. but he that is greateſt among you, let him be your ſeruant. No man can iuſtly ſay, this was ſpoken vnto Eccleſiaſticall perſons onely, but alſo to lay men, for ſo the text ſaith: <hi>Then Ieſus ſpake to the multitude, and to his Diſciples.</hi> 2. In the ſame chapter it appeareth, that our Sauiour did celebrate his laſt Supper immediately before he ſpake theſe wordes, but that ſtorie being ſet downe more plaine by the other Enangeliſt, hee ſaide: <hi>drinke you of this all,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat:</hi> 26.</note> which wordes were ſpoken onely to his Apoſtles, and yet, none but they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will ſo conſter them, as if they were ment onely of Eccleſiaſticall perſons. For, euen as the Cuppe in the holy Communion, did not appertaine onely vnto the Miniſterie, but alſo vnto the laitie; ſo humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is the Subiect of this ſpeech, is not commended onely to the Apoſtles, but to all men. So that, if the title of Lord belong not to the Apoſtles, neither doth it belong vnto ony other, becauſe theſe wordes doe indifferently concerne all.</p>
               <p>The ſecond queſtion is, whether in theſe wordes of our Sauiour any mention is made concerning the title of Lord, or no? Surely whoſoeuer ſhall ſay that the title of Lord is here forbidden, hee hath as litle iudgement in the Greeke tongue, as the man in the Goſpell, which was not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne men from trees. For the Greeke which is authenticall, becauſe it was written by the holy Ghoſt, hath no ſuch words as gracious Lords, but <hi>euergetai</hi> bountifull, or benefactors, or doers of good: they which bare rule ouer them are called well doers, but yee ſhall not be ſo. There cannot be one place of Scripture alledged betweene the firſt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the laſt of The <hi>Apocalips,</hi> to proue that Gods Miniſters may not be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lords, but ſome places may bee alledged to proue that they are Lords. Our Sauiour his ſelfe doth accept of that ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh:</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> of Lord giuen him by <hi>Nicod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus,</hi> when hee called him <hi>Rabbi,</hi> that is, my Lord. For <hi>Rabbi,</hi> as <hi>Pagnin</hi> ſheweth in his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10643:26"/> Lexicon, ſignifieth: <hi>Magiſtrum; honorabilem, inclytum, ob multiplices quibus po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>let dignitates,</hi> a Maiſter, an honourable <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 13.</note> perſon, a man that is eminent by reaſon of his manifold dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and places of honour which he holdeth. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſaith, the name <hi>Kurios</hi> Lord, doth of right belong vnto him, <hi>Vmeis phoneite me o didaſcales, caio Kurios, cai calos legete, eimigar.</hi> You call me Doctor, and Lord, and ye ſay wel, for ſo I am. Furthermore, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> accepted of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itle of <hi>Curios</hi> Lord, when it was giuen them by the keeper of the priſon, when hee fell downe before them, and ſaide: <hi>Kur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oi</hi> Lords, <hi>what muſt I doe to be ſaued?</hi> to whom they <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 30</note> anſwered: <hi>beleeue in the Lord Ieſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi> And a greater title then Lord is giuen to Gods Miniſters in his owne word, they are called Gods. For that of the Prophet: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 6. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 10. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſtandeth in the aſſemblie of Gods, and I haue ſaide ye are Gods,</hi> meaning of Princes and Iudges, our Sauiour his ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth of Miniſters. For, when the Iewes ſaide to him: <hi>For thy good worke wee ſtone thee not: but for blaſphemie, and that thou being a man, makeſt thy ſelfe God.</hi> Ieſus anſwered them: <hi>Is it not written in your Lawe, I ſaide yee are Gods? if hee call them Gods vnto whom the word of God is giuen, and the Scripture cannot be broken, ſay yee of him whom the Father hath ſanctified, and ſent into the world, thou blaſphemeſt, becauſe I ſayd: I am the Sonne of God?</hi> You ſee how in the whole courſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Miniſter and the Magiſtrate goe together, both of them are Gods annointed, both called Gods, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the perſon of God vpon earth: both Lords, becauſe they be the deputies and Leiftenants of him that is the Lord of Lords: to the ciuill Magiſtrate is eſpecially committed the temporall ſword, to the Miniſter the diſpenſation of the word. And you ſee here the reaſon plainly expreſſed, why our Sauiour calleth Miniſters Gods, becauſe vnto them the word of God was giuen, and the ſame word which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the miniſters vnder the law, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to the miniſters of the Goſpel, and muſt continue with them to the worldes end. The king is called <hi>Poimen,</hi> ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, ſo is the miniſter, &amp; in the originall tongues, <hi>paſcere,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 2.</note>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:10643:26"/> 
                  <hi>regere,</hi> to feede and to gouerne is all one And that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh tranſlation is corrupt, where it hath; <hi>ye ſhall not be called gratious Lords:</hi> it appeareth, not onely by the originall, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the analogy of faith: becauſe according to faith, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops may be Lords, as I haue ſhewed, and then much more gratious Lords: for elſe they were graceleſſe Lords. For this word grace, according to the Scriptures, is taken actiuely for the loue and fauour of the ſuperiour, which hee vouchſafeth the inferiour. So the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>By the grace of God, I am</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. <hi>Luk</hi> 2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>that I am:</hi> or elſe paſſiuely, for any good parts &amp; gifts in the inferiour, by which he is reſpected of his ſuperiour. So the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was ful of grace, the child Ieſus grew in grace: they all meruailed at the wordes of grace which proceeded out of his mouth, wee are freely iuſtified through his grace; if of grace, then not of works; we are ſaued by grace through faith. To euery one of vs is giuen grace, according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt. Do not neglect the grace which is conferred on thee by impoſition of hands. Let euery man <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet</hi> 4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> as hee hath receiued grace, miniſter the ſame one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that wee may come to the true expoſition of theſe wordes: <hi>There aroſe a controuerſie among them, who ſhould ſeeme to be the greateſt, &amp;c.</hi> In which ſtory, are two things to be obſerued: their example of ambition, which did ſtriue for ſuperiority, and our Sauiour, his doctrine of humility, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that ſuch ambition is found among the Gentiles, and ought not to bee among Chriſtians. The Kings of the Nations, ſaith hee, reigne ouer them: that is, ouer the Nations which are vnder them, and that by oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Muſculus</hi> haue ezpounded it, not according to iuſtice, as Gods word willeth them to doe, but after their own ſenſuall luſts and fleſhly deſires, and they are called <hi>(euergetai)</hi> doers of good, as the <hi>Ptolomes</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> two of them did ſername their own ſelues, albeit they were not doers of good, but of euill, and oppreſſors of their ſubiect Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this to chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he ſaith <hi>you ſhal not be called ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not reign as kings, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10643:27"/> gouerne as ſubiects, not tyrannically, but iuſtly, you ſhall not be called doers of good, but <hi>(cacoergoi)</hi> euill doers, and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours, although ye doe good, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh; <hi>Wee are reuiled, and yet we bleſſe, wee are perſecuted, and wee ſuffer,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 12. 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 38</note> 
                  <hi>we are euill ſpoken of, and we pray.</hi> It is your dutie to doe good, as it is ſaid of our Sauiour <hi>(dielthen euergeton)</hi> he went about doing good: yet you ſhall not haue the due praiſe of your well doing, as our Sauiour himſelfe was called Belzebub, a glutton, a drunkard, <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt an hypocrit, all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſeditious men, &amp;c: notwithſtanding they were all doers of good. So then, in this place is not forbidden honour and authority, but ambitious ſeeking of it, as when they ſtroue, and vniuſt vſing of it, as the Kings of the Nations did: as when he ſaith; <hi>The Scribes and Phariſies loue the chiefeſt places, &amp;c: and to be called Rabb, &amp;c:</hi> Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> vpon that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 8 <hi>In annot. maioribus.</hi>
                  </note> text, ſaith; The title of Rabbi, was giuen to ſuch as were Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours in the Chaldaean vniuerſities, as alſo which in <hi>Iudaea</hi> by impoſition of hands, were declared to be the wiſe men of the land, as alſo it was a title giuen to thoſe noble and wiſe men which were counſellers to King <hi>Dauid.</hi> And ſaith hee; <hi>When our Sauiour forbiddeth them: be not ye called Rabbi, for one is your Doctour, to wit, Chriſt, &amp;c: Ne vocemini, id eſt, nè ambiatis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim vetat Chriſtus ne ſuum honorem exhibeamus magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, vel doctoribus, ſed ambitionem damnat, vt declarat August: ſer: deverbis Domini ex Matthaei.</hi> 11. <hi>Be not you called Rabbi:</hi> that is, doe not you ambitiouſly ſeeke after that title; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe our Sauiour doth not forbid vs to giue due honour to the Magiſtrate and Doctour, but onely he forbiddeth the ambitious ſeeking after ſuch honour, as appeareth by Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> his expoſition. <hi>One is our Doctour,</hi> that is, the chief paſtour, the fountaine of all knowledge, according to that of the Prophet: <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lord. Call</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54. 13</note> 
                  <hi>no man your father:</hi> that is, nouriſh no man in his ambition, which glorieth in ſuch titles, <hi>respicit enim Iudaeorum conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, apud quos non modo Aboth, id eſt patres, ſed &amp; Abothenu, id eſt patres noſtri, ſalutabantur Rabbini:</hi> he hath reference to the cuſtome of the Iewes, among whom the Rabbines would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10643:27"/> not be contented to be called fathers, but our fathers. Ye are brethren, that is, beate downe the pride of them which exalt themſelues aboue their brethren. For otherwiſe it is lawfull to call them fathers which are fathers. So the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> called <hi>Eliſaeus</hi> his father: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will haue an elder to <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 6. 21. . 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 15.</note> bee rebuked as a father, and hee calleth himſelfe a father of them whom he hath inſtructed in the word. As for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, they did not exerciſe ciuill iuriſdiction, according to forme of humane lawes, as Magiſtrates in Courts of iuſtice vſe to doe, partly becauſe they being to trauell through the world, had no certaine abiding place, and partly becauſe Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Iuſtices are ſubordinate vnto Kings &amp; Princes, and haue their commiſſion from them, as our Sauiour ſpeaketh: <hi>Quis me conſtituit Iudicem?</hi> who hath appointed mee to be a Iudge ouer you? But all Kings &amp; Princes were at that time <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 14</note> infidells, and therefore would not call them to ſuch offices, which if they had been called vnto, they might lawfully haue executed. And yet it may be iuſtified, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted ciuill iuſtice vpon <hi>Saphira,</hi> when hee pronounced ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death againſt her, ſaying: <hi>Behold, the feete of them</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>which haue buried thy husband, are at the doore, and ſhal carry thee out:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> vpon <hi>Elymas,</hi> when hee pronounced ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> of depriuation of his ſight, ſaying: <hi>Thou ſhalt be blinde, and not ſee the Sunne for a ſeaſon:</hi> although outward forme of proceeding was wanting; like to that example of <hi>Dauid</hi> a King which ſaid of the man which brought tydings of <hi>Sauls</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 15. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 33.</note> death, without any further proceſſe or courſe of law: <hi>Goe, fall vpon him;</hi> and he ſmote him that he died: and of <hi>Samuel</hi> which tooke <hi>Agag,</hi> &amp; he wed him in pieces: and of <hi>Ioiada</hi> the prieſt, which when <hi>Athalia</hi> the Queene in the Temple cried; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, treaſon, without any iudiciall examination, or kinde <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11. 15.</note> of proceeding, commanded the Captaines immediately to carry her out and kill her.</p>
               <p>And that theſe things may not ſeeme ſtrange, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> foretolde ſo much. For the <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6</note> Apoſtle writeth in this manner: <hi>Hee hath made vs able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the new Teſtament, not of the letter, but of the ſpirit, for the</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:10643:28"/> 
                  <hi>letter killeth, but the ſpirit giueth life.</hi> If then the miniſtration of death, written with letters, and ingrauen in ſtone was glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not able to beholde <hi>Moſes</hi> his face, for the glory of his countenance, which glory is done away, how ſhall not the miniſtration of the ſpirit be more glorious? For, if the miniſtery of condemnation was glorious, much more doth the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe exceede in glory: for if that which ſhould bee aboliſhed was glorious, much more ſhall that which remaineth bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. In which wordes are to be obſerued two things: the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſis or contrariety, betweene the Miniſters of both the Teſtaments, and then the correſpondency and agreement betweene them both: that is, wherein they conſent, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they diſſent. They diſagree in theſe points, <hi>the letter and the ſpirit, death and life, condemnation and righteouſneſſe, that which was to be aboliſhed, and that which is to abide vntill the end of the world:</hi> and yet both agree in glorie, but the ſpirit excelleth the letter, life death, righteouſneſſe, condemnation, that which is that which is not. Therefore the miniſterie of the Goſpel by an argument, <hi>a minori ad maius,</hi> is alſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by ſo much more glorious then the miniſterie of the law, by how much it is more excellent then the law. The queſtion is now, what is meant by glory? And becauſe men may be reſolued of that point, the text it ſelfe doth make it plaine, it was outward. The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Moſes</hi> his face, for the glory of his countenance. After he had talked with God, the skin of his face ſhone ſo bright, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17</note> that they were afraid to come neare him. And that ſheweth what is meant by the glory of God which <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee, when anſwer was made, hee ſhould <hi>ſee his backe parts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but not his face.</hi> And it is ſhewed by example, how our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified bodies ſhal looke after the reſurrection, when the face of our Sauiour being transfigured, did ſhine like the Sunne. The Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes: Thou ſhalt make holy garments for thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> 
                  <hi>brother</hi> Aaron, <hi>glorius &amp; beautifull, of gold, blew ſilke, purple, &amp;c.</hi> The holineſſe of his garments conſiſted in this, that they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10643:28"/> were conſecrated to an holy vſe, they were for the prieſt to weare in his miniſtration, the glory of them is ſpecified to be the outward beauty, that they were of glod, ſilk, purple, &amp;c. <hi>Solomon</hi> in his glory was not like a lily in the field, but wherin <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomons</hi> glory co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſted, no man is ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: that is, in his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pompe, riches, ſeruice, honourable retinew, the <hi>adifice</hi> of his Temple, the world did admire him. So it is plaine, that the prieſthoode of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the glory of it conſiſted in the riches of the Temple, the large poſſeſsions of the <hi>Leuites,</hi> their authority and worldly reputation, the high Prieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing next in place of honour vnto the king. But how the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the Goſpel ſhould exceede them in glory; the Prophets haue foretolde, and eſpecialle <hi>Eſay,</hi> where he ſaith: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>Thine heart ſhall be astoniſhed, and inlarged, becauſe the multude of the Sea ſhall be conuerted vnto thee, and the riches of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall come vnto thee, the multitude of Camel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſhall couer thee, the Dromedaries of Midian and of Ephah, they of Sheba ſhall bring gold and incenſe, and ſhew forth the praiſe of the Lord, &amp;c. Surely the Iſles ſhall wayte for me, and the Shippes of</hi> Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis, <hi>as at the beginning, that they may bring thy ſonnes from farre, and their ſiluer, and their gold with them to the name of the Lord, and to the holy one of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>becauſe he hath glorified thee. The ſonnes of ſtrangers ſhall build vp thy walls, and their Kings ſhall minister vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, &amp;c. The Nation of the Kingdome that will not ſerue thee, ſhall periſh, and thoſe Nations ſhall be vtterly deſtroyed, the glory of</hi> Lebanon <hi>ſhall come vnto thee, the firre, the elme, the boxe, to beautifie the place of my ſanctuarie, for I will glorifie the place of my feete. The ſonnes of them that afflicted thee, ſhall come and bowe vnto thee, all they that despiſed thee, ſhall fall downe at the ſoules of thy feete, &amp;c: Thou ſhalt ſucke the milke of the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>thou ſhalt ſucke the breastes of Kings, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Reader may be yet better ſatisfied. <hi>Flacius Iilyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In claui ſcripturae.</note> diuideth glory to be two folde, the one of God, the other of men: and as for the glory of God, it cannot be vnderſtood
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10643:29"/> in this place, but of men onely; becauſe hee ſpeaketh one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the glory of the Miniſters of the olde and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which were onely men. Againe, hee diuideth the glory of men, either into that which is eternall in heauen, or temporall vpon the earth: but the latter onely is vnderſtood, becauſe it is the glory of the miniſtery, which miniſtery is temporall, and muſt ceaſe after this life, euen as alſo then faith and hope muſt ceaſe, onely loue muſt indure. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he diuideth this temporall glory of men, into <hi>gloriam fame</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; bonitatis rei;</hi> the glory of wordes, and of matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the glory of wordes or fame, which conſiſteth in the fame and good report of other men, which is chiefly in them which doe glorifie vs, and not in our ſelues which are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified and magnified, but the glory which is not in wordes, but ſubſtance, which indeed is the cauſe why men doe praiſe and magnifie vs, is our riches, honour, authority, all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ornaments, which ſtirre vp the outward ſenſes, and mens affections, to admiration of our perſons, places, and calling, is onely to be vnderſtood in this place, as appeareth by theſe reaſons. Firſt, the glory of fame is defined by <hi>Illyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and alſo by <hi>Melancthon,</hi> in his common places, to be: <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatio conſcientiae nostrae rectè iudicantis, &amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>crum rectè iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium:</hi> The teſtimony of a good conſcience, approuing vs that we haue walked ſincerely, and the report of other men, conſenting in iudgement with vs, that wee haue ſo walked. But in that ſenſe, wee cannot be more glorious then <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prieſtes of the old Teſtament, becauſe they were men of as holy life as wee, and walked euery way as ſincerely in their calling, as wee doe in our vocation, and were as pleaſing to God, and as well approoued of Gods people as we be. Secondly, it were vnworthy of the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the holy Ghoſt, to play the ſo phiſter in this place, and to vſe aequiuocation of the word glory, as if by their glory and ours, he did not vnderſtand one and the ſame thing: for then it were no iuſt compariſon. For the things which be compared together, muſt agree in that thing in which they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10643:29"/> be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared: therfore, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared in glory, they muſt agree in the ſame glory; only they muſt differ <hi>ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magis &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> being compared not in the poſitiue, but in the compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue degreee, one muſt be more glorious then another. So then, the glory of one being outward in pompe and ſtate, the glory of the other muſt alſo be ſo, but in a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if ſome men ſhould be ſo ignorant as to ſay, that the glory of our miniſtery conſiſteth in this, that it is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the ſpirit, of life, of righteouſneſſe, and of that which muſt remaine. I anſwer; that cannot be, for then the glory of the miniſtery of the olde Teſtament, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in letters, death, condemnation, &amp;c: but that is diſproued by the text it ſelfe, which ſheweth that theſe things were the ſubiect of that miniſtery, but the glory conſiſted in the brightneſſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> his face: therefore I ſay; ſpirit, life, righteouſneſſe, are the ſubiect of our miniſtery, and not the glory of it: &amp; the cauſe why it ought to be ſo much the more glorious then the old prieſthood was. Fourthly, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſcope and drift of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in that place, it was to magnifie himſelfe, and credit his calling, that ſo it might not be brought into contempt, as poore and beggarly, which were inglorious. For, ſaith thee: <hi>Doe wee beginne to praiſe our ſelues? Neede we as ſome other, an epistle of commendation?</hi> Hee anſwereth: that hee needeth not to commend himſelfe, hee needeth not mans commendation to credite his miniſtery, for as much as his calling is of ſufficient credite of it ſelfe, and his owne perſon credited by it three manner of waies. Firſt, by the Corinthians themſelues, to whom hee did miniſter. Secondly, by that which was inward in his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, as ſpirit, life, righteouſneſſe. Thirdly, by that which was outward, and apparent to the eye, and that was glorie.</p>
               <p>Now, leſt any man ſhould obiect out of Saint <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Theophilactus, Aquinas,</hi> and others, that in their interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that place of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> they affirme that the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10643:30"/> glory of his miniſtery, was no ſuch glory as was viſible and ſubiect to outward ſenſes. I confeſſe that when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote that epiſtle, it was not ſo of fact, although it was ſo of right. It could not be then outwardly glorious, by reaſon of the preſent perſecution, the miniſtery of the Goſpel being not eſtabliſhed by Princes. Therefore the Apoſtle ſpake not ſo much of the glory which then was, as of that which in the peace and proſperity of the Church, ſhould afterward be, when the world was conuerted. For his words are theſe: <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mallon e diaconia tou pneumatos eſtai en doxe?</hi> how ſhall not the miniſtration of the ſpirit bee more glorious? where hee ſpeaketh in the future tence, as of a thing in due time to be performed, and not preſent. And therefore, where he ſpeaketh in the preſent tence in the next verſe; <hi>Pollo mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon periſſeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i e diaconia tes dicaioſunes en doxe;</hi> much more doth the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe exceede in glory, as it is a figure called <hi>enalloge temporis,</hi> where one tenſe is vſed for another, as it appeared by the euent (which is the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of all prophecies) when the riches, authority, and outward pompe of the Church was increaſed. And yet it cannot be ſaid, that the miniſtery of the Goſpel was without outward glory, in the extreameſt pouerty of the Church, for as much as the Apoſtles at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had all the riches of the Church layed at their feete, and at their owne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and when worldly promotion was moſt of all wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they had the gift of working miracles, which was a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory and countenance to their miniſtery, then any Kings or earthly meanes could giue vnto them. St. <hi>Peter,</hi> his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow was more glorious and more honoured then the body and perſon of any Prince. Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> napkins and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchers, and ſuch like ragges which came from his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 93.</note> were of more account then the purple robes, and golde and ſiluer of earthly Kings. And this gift of working miracles, continued as the portion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haeritance of Chriſt his Miniſters, vntill they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined peace, and ſo were indewed with worldely
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10643:30"/> poſſeſſions, and honours, which were to countenance their miniſterie in the place of miracles which did ceaſe. So that ſtill the miniſtery of the Goſpell was outwardly glorious and honourable, not vile, abiect, or contemptible. The Lord of his mercy continue the ſtate of it vnto his own glory, to the worlds end.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ANSWER TO THE TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Croſſe in Baptiſme,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into this Syllogiſme.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <item>"No humane ordinance becomming an idoll, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully "be vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
                  <item>"But the ſigne of the Croſſe being an humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, "is become an idoll. </item>
                  <item>"Therefore The ſigne of the Croſſe may not be lawfully vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="defense">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:10643:31"/>
            <head>OF THE SIGNE of the Croſſe in Baptiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as wee be no plaintiues, but defendants, neither doth it belong vnto vs, as opponents to obiect, or allege any arguments for proofe of that truth which is already eſtabliſhed, but onely, as reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondents to anſwere ſuch obiections, as are brought by our aduerſaries to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that hold whereof wee are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: we will therefore, ſo farre as by the Lawes of diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we are bound, make anſwer to all points in particular, as they are vrged againſt vs. And therefore, firſt of all we will examine the title of the booke which is contracted into this Syllogiſme.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>"No humane ordinance becomming an idoll, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully "be vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
               <item>"But the ſigne of the Croſſe being an humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, "is become an idoll. </item>
               <item>"Therefore The ſigne of the Croſſe may not be lawfully vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Becauſe this Syllogiſme is intended to be in the firſt figure, we wiſh the author had explaned his meaning, in what mood it is concluded? becauſe, as it is ſet downe in theſe Engliſh wordes, it is vncertaine whether it be in <hi>CELARENT</hi> or in <hi>FERLO,</hi> in one of them it muſt be, for elſe it is no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Syllogiſme. If it bee in <hi>CELARENT,</hi> then the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10643:31"/> 
               <hi>MINOR</hi> muſt be vnderſtood to be vniuerſall affirmatiue, and then, theſe wordes: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>The ſigne of the Croſſe being an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinance is become an idoll,</hi>
               </q> are equiualent to theſe: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Euery ſigne of the Croſſe is an humane ordinance, and euery ſigne of the Croſſe is become an idoll.</hi>
               </q> Which, if it be ſo vnderſtood, then the <hi>MINOR</hi> is to be denied as vntrue. For, the viſible and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent ſigne of the Croſſe, which appeared to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, by which he was conuerted to the Chriſtian faith, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb: dè vitâ Conſt: lib:</hi> 1. <hi>cap:</hi> 22.</note> was neither an humane ordinance, becauſe it was the worke of God, and not of men, it appeared in heauen, and not on earth, neither was it an idoll, becauſe it was neither worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, nor ſhewed to that end that it ſhould be worſhipped (the Author his ſelfe in his Treatiſe ſaith,<q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>nothing is an idol, vnleſſe it be worſhipped)</hi>
               </q> neither was the inuiſible and tranſient ſigne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech:</hi> 9. 4.</note> of the Croſſe in the Propheſie of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> any humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance becauſe God commanded it, nor any idoll, becauſe it was not worſhipped. Onely it was a marke of them which were ordained to ſaluation, and it was to be ſigned in their forheads by the Prieſt in the Surpleſſe, or linnen Ephod, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the blood of the paſchal Lambe which was ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.</note> vpon the dore cheekes in <hi>Egypt</hi> by the Angell, which was to paſſe ouer the houſes ſo marked, and to ſaue them from death which were in the houſes ſo marked. And that in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> reuelation was but a reſemblance of them both, where the elect had <hi>the ſeale of the liuing God in their forheads.</hi> This <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc:</hi> 7. 4.</note> ſigne in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> was the ſigne of the Croſſe, becauſe it was the Hebrew charactar, <hi>T AV,</hi> which letter as it is now prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Alphabet, reſembleth the Gallowes, or inſtrument of execution of thieues and murtherers. But, as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſheweth: when this propheſie was firſt written, the Iewes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom: in Ezech:</hi> 9.</note> then the ſame letters which the <hi>Samaritans</hi> had, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they were deuiſed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Hebrew <hi>T A V</hi> was of the ſame forme which the Greeke <hi>T AV</hi> is of at this day, which is ſuch a Croſſe in forme, as that which was,, <hi>ara mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> the Altar of the world, vpon which our Sauiour Chriſt was crucified. And that afterward it was changed into this ordinary forme of Gallowes by <hi>Ezra,</hi> after the captiuitie,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10643:32"/> which altred all the letters in the Alphabet into this forme which is now vſed in all Hebrewe impreſsions, that the letters of the beleeuing Iewes might differ from the letters of the vnbeleeuing <hi>Samaritans.</hi> The ſigne of the croſſe in the forheads of the elect was as eſpeciall in the dayes of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> as the marke of the liuing God in their forheads, in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> reuelation, &amp; the ſprinkling of the dore-cheekes in the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and did outwardly ſhewe that none could eſcape death, which had not <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>interiùs expreſſam fidem crucis &amp; mortis Chriſti, quiqùe exteriùs Ceriſium intrepidè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteretur,</hi>
               </q> an inward impreſſion in their hearts, of the Croſſe and death of our Sauiour Chriſt, and made an outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant profeſsion of the ſame to the view of the world, to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w that they were not aſhamed of their crucified Lord Ieſus, nor afeard to drinke of his cup, and be baptiſed with his baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>which was calix amaritudinis, and baptiſmus ſanguinis, and</hi>
               </q> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20. 23.</note> 
               <hi>crucis,</hi> the cup of bitternes, and baptiſme of blood and martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of the Croſſe &amp; tribulation. Now, the Chriſtians in the infancie of the Church, did ſigne themſelues with this <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>TA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> or ſigne of the Croſſe, <hi>in eâ parte vbi eſt ſignum pudoris vt non puderet eos crucifixi,</hi>
               </q> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> witneſſeth, in their<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De verbis apostoli Ser:</hi> 8. <hi>De cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rudibus. cap:</hi> 20.</note> very forheads, to teſtifie their profeſsion, in imitation of the examples of the holy Scriptures which I haue recited, as the ſame Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> witneſſeth, and that before popery had crept into the Church, witnes <hi>Tertullian,</hi> which liued within two hundred yeares after our Sauiour. And in the imitation of theſe examples, the ſigne of the croſſe is continued among vs, to bee ſigned vpon the forheads of them which are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and that without any worſhip or diuine honour done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, therefore it is no idoll.</p>
            <p>But if this Syllogiſme be in <hi>FERIO,</hi> as according to the rules of Logick it ought to be, becauſe it is an indefinite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in matter contingent, then is the <hi>MINOR</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and likewiſe the concluſion, and then it is all one, as if he had ſaide: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Some ſigne of the Croſſe is an humane ordinance, and ſome ſigne of the Croſſe is become an idoll, therefore ſome ſigne of the Croſſe is not to be vſed in Gods ſeruice.</hi>
               </q> And then
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10643:32"/> we grant both the propoſition &amp; the concluſion, as no diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage vnto vs, becauſe he concludeth nothing againſt vs. For our ſigne is neither that which man hath diuiſed, neither that which is worſhipped (the Author his ſelfe doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in his Treatiſe, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>that wee doe not worſhippe the Croſſe in Baptiſme, nor any way make an idoll of it).</hi>
               </q> Neither can any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular concluſion ouerthrowe a generall point of doctrine, as if becauſe one Croſſe is ſo, therefore all Croſſes ſhould be ſo. A generall is not to bee concluded by a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, but a particular by a general.<q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi> Syllogizari non eſt ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulari.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hauing anſwered the matter which is contingent, and the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie which is indefinite, it followeth that we examine the forme of this ſyllogiſme, and lay open the manifold defectes of it, to ſhewe how indeede it is no true ſyllogiſme, but a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie, which that we may the better effect, we muſt firſt ſcan euery word in order, as they bee placed in the Syllogiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all therefore, where he ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>No humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance being become an idoll may bee vſed in Gods ſeruice.</hi> 
               </q> Iwould knowe then whether a diuine ordinance being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an idoll may be vſed in Gods ſeruice? If it may, then the bread in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, which is Gods ordinance being hallowed by the Prieſt, eleuated vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar in the Maſſe, adored by the people, being put in the pix, and reſerued, may bee afterward broken by the hands of the Miniſter, and deliuered to the people in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Sacrament of the Lords Table. I hope, to that queſtion hee will anſwere negatiuely, therefore this caution which hee putteth in, to wit, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>No humane ordinance,</hi>
               </q> is but ſuperfluous, and might as wel haue beene left out of the ſyllogiſme. Nay, he might as well haue ſaide: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>No diuine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance becomming an idoll, may be retained in the Church, much</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Numb:</hi> 21 9. 2. <hi>Reg:</hi> 18. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>leſſe vſed in diuine ſeruice.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For the braſen ſerpent being Gods ordinance, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to bee a moſt liuely type and figure of our Sauiour Chriſt, when they burnt incenſe vnto it, was defaced
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10643:33"/> by <hi>Ezechias,</hi> and for ſo doing hee was commended, to haue done vprightly in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that his Father <hi>Dauid</hi> had done. And yet, I ſay, the idoll being remoued, Gods ordinance ought ſtill to ſtand. The bread which is conſecrated, eleuated, and adored in the Maſſe, is vnfit to bee taken and eaten in the Lords Supper, and yet bread is ſtill to be vſed in that Supper without ſuch eleuation, and adoration. And as for the braſen Serpent, here is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene that and this: Had the people ceaſed to burne incenſe vnto it, yet being broken and defaced, no other like to that was to be erectect, for as much as that was but a temporall ordinance of God for that preſent time, when they were ſtunge with fierie Serpents in the Wilderneſſe, ſeruing for that vſe to heale them when they looked vppon it, which vertue of healing afterward ceaſed, but, had Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents ſtill ſtunge them, and the ſight of a braſen Serpent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſtill for healing of ſuch woundes, a newe braſen ſerpent which was neuer worſhipped, might haue beene made in the place of it which was defaced.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I would knowe alſo,<q rend="margQuotes"> whether <hi>an humane ordinance being no idoll may bee vſed in Gods ſeruice?</hi>
               </q> To that Maiſter <hi>Iacob</hi> anſwereth negatiuely, in his Booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, likewiſe, the Author of the Treatiſe of diuine worſhippe, therefore this clauſe: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>becomming an idoll,</hi>
               </q> was but idle, and might very well haue beene ſpared, and it ſtandeth but in the place of a ciphre, or rather an idoll it ſelfe, becauſe, as the Apoſtle writeth: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>idoium nihil eſt,</hi>
               </q> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 84.</note> 
               <hi>an idoll is nothing,</hi> and this alſo ſtandeth for nothing. Let the framer therefore of this ſyllogiſme ſpeake whether hee meaneth: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>in ſenſu diuiſo, becauſe it is an humane ordinance? or becauſe it is an idoll? or elſe, becauſe ioyned both together in ſenſu coniuncto, it is both an humane ordinance and an idoll, it is vnfit for Gods ſeruice?</hi>
               </q> If hee make it a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the ſigne of the Croſſe ſhould bee croſſed out of the s;eruice Booke, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>el eo nomine,</hi>
               </q> becauſe it was an humane ordinance, then hee might haue ſpared to make mention of an idoll, if he meane <hi>eò nomine,</hi> becauſe it was an idoll, then
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10643:33"/> might hee haue ſpared to ſpeake of humane ordinance, as wordes idlely put in. <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura quod aequè benè fieri poteſt pèr pauciora.</hi>
               </q> If yee meane an humane ordinance might haue beene vſed, ſo it were not become an idoll, or an idoll, had it not beene an humane ordinance, or otherwiſe, if he ment none of them both, then theſe two were not well ioyned together in this ſyllogiſme. But, as for our ſigne of the Croſſe, with which we ſigne infants in Baptiſme, wee doe not in ſo doing imitate the examples of men, but the holy Scripture, and ſo denye it to bee an humane ordinance, wee adore it not outwardly with the body, nor inwardly in our mindes, and therefore wee denie it to be an idoll (for ſtill I builde vppon that ground of the Author of this ſyllogiſme, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>that nothing is an idoll vnleſſe it be worſhipped)</hi>
               </q> therefore, no worſhip, no idoll. And therefore notwithſtanding this ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, nothing hindereth but that it may bee vſed in the Sacrament of Baptiſme, which is a part of GODS ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the argument doth not followe, that becauſe the bread which is adored by the Papiſts, is become an idoll, therefore the bread which is not adored by vs is an idoll, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sunne and Moone were as Gods to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens which worſhipped them, therefore they are Gods to vs which vouchſafe them no worſhip, becauſe <hi>Gedeons Ephod</hi> was an idoll to them which worſhipped it, being hung vp in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud:</hi> 8. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Ophra,</hi> therefore that <hi>Ephod</hi> which the Prieſt did weare in <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple and not worſhip, was an Idoll in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> becauſe the altars which were erected for ſacrifice in the high places, &amp; that vpon which <hi>Iereboam</hi> offred incenſe, were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg:</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Ioſua</hi> 22. 10.</note> of idolatry, therefore the altar which the two tribes of <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and halfe <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> erected to be a witneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues and the other tribes, vpon which no ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice nor incenſe was offred, nor intended to be offred, ſhould alſo be held for a monument of idolatry, becauſe the name of Ieſus was abuſed and vainely taken by the coniurers, it might not be lawfully vſed by the Apoſtles: ſo the argument <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act:</hi> 19. 13.</note> doth not followe, that becauſe the ſigne of the Croſſe is an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10643:34"/> idoll to the Papiſts which worſhip it, therefore it ſhould be an idoll to vs which worſhip it not. The Author his ſelfe, as before I haue ſhewed, ſaith <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>nothing is an idoll but quatenù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is worſhipped:</hi>
               </q> and againe, hee freeth vs from the crime of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, ſaying that <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>our Church aſcribeth no worſhip vnto it,</hi>
               </q> therefore hee doth not iuſtly call it by the name of an idoll; and apply it vnto vs. Their abuſe cannot diſanull our lawfull vſe, and whatſoeuer may by them bee abuſed, may by vs bee lawfully vſed, therefore their ſuperſtition cannot make a nullitie of our ſincere and true deuotion. As the Croſſe hath beene abuſed, ſo hath Gods Temple beene profaned in the dayes of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> and in the dayes of our Sauiour Chriſt, yet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezechi:</hi> 8: <hi>Ioh:</hi> 2.</note> neither of them would haue the Temple to bee ſuppreſſed. Maſſes haue beene ſaide in all our Churches, ſhall wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be as the Browniſts which refuſe to come to Church to heare our dinine ſeruice? They are the ſame Churches <hi>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> the Croſſe is not, therefore the argument followeth <hi>á maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ad mious,</hi> the Churches may bee as well remoued as the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the ſigne of the Croſſe he ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>is become an idoll,</hi>
               </q> therefore he denieth it to haue beene originally an idoll as the golden colfe was which was erected in <hi>Horeb,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex:</hi> 32. 4.</note> he denieth it to haue beene originally an idoll, he muſt needes ouerthrowe that firſt ground which hee layed in his <hi>MINOR</hi> propoſition, where hee affirmed that it was an humane ordinance. For the Author of the booke of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation alledging the authoritie of <hi>Vrſinus</hi> in his expoſition <note place="margin">Maiſter Iacob.</note> vpon the ſecond commaundement, and the Author of the treatiſe of diuine worſhip, affirme that all humane inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church are idolatry, becauſe they impugne the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commaundement of the firſt Table, and that the word of God is ſo perfect and all-ſufficient of it ſelfe, that man may ordaine nothing in the Church, but all additions of men are idolatry. I conclude therefore, out of their own wordes, that if it be become an idoll, it was no humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and if it were an humane ordinance, it could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an idol, becauſe it was an idol <hi>ab initio,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10643:34"/> of it. And therfore, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>it is become an idol,</hi> he muſt grant, that it was God ordinance. And ſo I deny not but the holieſt creatures in the world may become idolls by mans worſhipping the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ſo is the bread in the ſacrament, ſo is the beginning of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpel, <hi>In principio erat verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> being hung about childrens necks, with certaine charmes of ſorcery to keep the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from ſtumbling, become an idol. And the 18. verſe of the 50. Pſalme: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>When thou ſaweſt a theefe, thou didſt run with him:</hi>
               </q> being vſed with other circumſtances by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurations to finde out ſtolen goods, which is to aſcribe diuine power to theſe creatures. But, for as much as originally, the vſe of the Croſſe was lawfull, we doe retaine it in our Church as originally it was vſed: and therefore wee may iuſtifie the vſe of it.</p>
            <p>Fiftly therefore, whereas hee ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>that which is an idoll may not be vſed in Gods ſeruice:</hi>
               </q> it maketh nothing againſt vs which haue proued the Croſſe to be no idoll. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that I may lay open the manifolde imperfections of this kinde of argumentation, to ſhew that it is no lawfull <hi>ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme,</hi> but a flat <hi>paralogiſme,</hi> in it I will diſcouer foure <hi>falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> And that I may not be like them, which as it is in the prouerbe, <hi>will ſpell law, and conſter logicke,</hi> I muſt be forced to vſe ſuch termes as belong to the Logitians, which cannot be well expreſſed in Engliſh, that I may obſerue the lawes of ſchooles. Out of the premiſſes which before I haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Firſt, there is <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>fallacia à dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter, quia in concluſione falſo id tribuitur rei ſimplicitèr conſideratae, quod in praemiſſis tributum fuit aliquâ conditione, ſeu determinatione &amp; circumſtantiâ,</hi>
               </q> as <hi>Abetzon</hi> ſpeaketh: In the concluſion, the ſigne of the Croſſe is condemned as ſimply vnlawfull, being ſimply conſidered without any reſpect of worſhip, which in the premiſſes is not vnderſtood but vpon circumſtances, and conditions of diuine worſhip to be aſcribed vnto it.</p>
            <p>Secendly, it is a <hi>paralogiſme,</hi> called <hi>ignoratio Elenchi,</hi> the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that fallacy, <hi>quià non eſt idem respectus, res non intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad idem ſecundum idem ſimiliter &amp; eodem tempore:</hi> there is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10643:35"/> not one and the ſelfe ſame reſpect, but diuers, the thing is not alike, but diuerſly vnderſtoode, it is not referred to one and the ſame things, according to the ſame, after the ſame maner, and at the ſame time, but all theſe circumſtances are different one from another.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>fallacia no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſae pro cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â,</hi>
               </q> ſuch a fallacy wherin that is taken for a cauſe, which is no cauſe: the abuſe of them which worſhip it, is here alleaged for a cauſe why it may not be lawfully vſed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, which their abuſe is no cauſe at al.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>fallacia accidentis,</hi>
               </q> a fallacy by reaſon of the accident which is included in that which belongeth onely vnto the ſubſtance, and ought to bee vnderſtood without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch accident. For he draweth his argument from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, which was meerely accidentall vnto the Croſſe, vnto the nature of the Croſſe it ſelfe, as <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>idolum fit, ergo verè ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt.</hi>
               </q> It is among ſome vſed as an idoll, therefore proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and originally the thing it ſelfe is an idoll. They doe <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>à praeteritis accidentibus aut euentis ad praeſentiam rei argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari;</hi>
               </q> draw their arguments from the accidental euents which are paſſed, vnto the thing as among vs it is now vſed: as for example, becauſe the ſigne of the Croſſe was worſhipped in the time of ignorance and ſuperſtition among Papiſts, that therefore it is now worſhipped among the Proteſtants, after the reformation of the Church.</p>
            <p>To leaue the title of the booke, and come to the tract it ſelfe. For proofe of the <hi>MAIOR,</hi> hee alleageth Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> authority, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Babes, keepe your ſelues from idolls:</hi>
               </q> as if that were a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. 21</note> good argument; we muſt keepe our ſelues from idolis, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee may not make the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme: which before I haue ſhewed to be no idoll, which is but <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio principij,</hi>
               </q> a begging of the queſtion. But for explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onof this text of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> he vndertaketh two things: firſt, to ſet downe the definition of an idoll: and ſecondly, to limit vs how farre wee are to keepe our ſelues from idolls, and therein he preſſeth vs with the authority of learned <hi>Zanche,</hi> when his ſelfe refuſeth not onely to ſtand to the authority of learned <hi>Caluin,,</hi> and learned <hi>Beza,</hi> and learned <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> but renounceth all other humane authorities, which are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10643:35"/> by vs alleaged againſt him, ſaying; he will ſtand to no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, but to the canonicall Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But to come to the definition of an idoll, hee defineth it to be, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>A quicquid praetèr Deum diuino honore colitur,</hi>
               </q> a whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye wil beſides God, if it be worſhipped with diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And he that will define an idoll to be <hi>à quicquid,</hi> will not refuſe to ſay <hi>à quidlibet,</hi> whatſoeuer his owne idle braine ſhall apprehend. Hee might rather haue ſaid with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, it is <hi>à nihil,</hi> then <hi>à quicquid,</hi> a new nothing, rather then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing, <hi>Scimus quià idolum nihil eſt in mundo,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4</note> we know that an idoll is nothing in the world. For though in matter it be ſomewhat, as wood, or ſtone, &amp;c: yet in forme it is nothing, becauſe it repreſenteth that which is not, as were the idolls of <hi>Mercury, lupiter,</hi> and ſuch like. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it differeth from an image, which repreſenteth that which is comprehended within the vniuerſality or nature of things, as the Schoolemen call it, as the image of a man, of a lyon, and ſuch like. But, becauſe it pleaſeth him to confound idols and images, which in nature doe differ: yet for as much as they ſerue for one purpoſe in this place, and the worſhip of either of them is a breach of the ſecond commandement, we will be contented to comprehend them both in one defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. And for as much as euery definition muſt conſiſt of <hi>à Genus,</hi> and that which is <hi>loco differentiae,</hi> at the leaſt, I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile that he doth call it <hi>à quicquid,</hi> and ſo make it <hi>à tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> as if it were in no <hi>praeaicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> For in that God ſaith: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make ſculptile aut ſimulacrum; any grauen image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing, &amp;c: thou ſhalt not bow downe to it nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>it:</hi> by theſe words it is plaine, that it is in the predicament or action, and out of it may be gathered this definition; that it is the workemanſhippe of a mans hand, whether carued, painted, molton, or facioned howſoeuer by the art of man, whether in the ayre, as the ſigne of the Croſſe <hi>tranſient,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as the Croſſe of wood which is <hi>permanent,</hi> repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſom ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or figme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to which we aſcribe diuine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent, we giue diuine honor. And wheras the author replieth, that then the worſhip of Angells, ſoules of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10643:36"/> iuſt men, and inuiſible ſpirits, were no idolatry. I anſwer, that ſuch worſhippe is a breach of the firſt commandement; <hi>Non habebis Deos alienos coram me: thou ſhat it haue no other Gods beſides mee:</hi> as alſo the worſhipping of the Sunne and Moone, which are the workemanſhip of God, and not of men.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond, where he ſaith: we muſt keep our ſelues both <hi>à cultu &amp; ab vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> idoli,</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worſhip of the idol, &amp; alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other vſe of it, in ſo much that we muſt not reteine it amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs: his own ſelf doth clear vs that we do not <hi>colere,</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it. And as for the vſe of it, which he ſaith; may be either <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>ciuill, as for ſtory, Princes banners, coignes, or elſe religious,</hi>
               </q> it is an idle diſtinction, for it is repugnant to the nature and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of an idoll, that it ſhould be ciuill. Idolls are made for diuine worſhip, and for no other vſe: therefore for Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall and religious vſes onely, and beeing not ſo vſed, they are no idolls, as the author his ſelfe confeſſeth. If hee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 11.</note> meane by the vſe of idolls, the bare retaining of them in the Church without any worſhip, as in many Churches of the Lutherans, where the images, which hee calleth idolls, doe ſtand in the Temples for ornaments onely: It is eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, we remoued them out of our Churches, and defaced them long ſince. But he ſaith; that by religious vſe of idolls, he meaneth: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>when any thing of mens deuiſe being worſhipped as an idoll, is vſed in the worſhip of God.</hi>
               </q> For anſwer whereof, we vſe no ſuch thing in our ſeruice: the Croſſe which we vſe in Baptiſme, is not worſhipped at all.</p>
            <p>Yet, ſaith hee: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>this point is farther ſtrengthened by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which forbiddeth not onely to worſhip, but alſo to make an image ad cultum, or for religious vſe.</hi>
               </q> In which words, he ſhould doe well to ſee his owne weakneſſe, or rather folly. I doe not deny, but as it is vnlawfull to worſhip it, ſo it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to make it <hi>ad cultum,</hi> that another ſhould worſhip it, as <hi>Demetrius</hi> the ſiluer-ſmith and his fellowes did, which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.</note> made ſhrines and images for <hi>Diana,</hi> her Temple. But, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hee ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>it is forbidden to make any ſimilitude ad cultum, or for religious vſe;</hi>
               </q> if he make theſe Engliſh words, <hi>for religious</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:10643:36"/> 
               <hi>vſe,</hi> to be an interpretation of theſe Latine wordes, <hi>ad cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> as if they were but the ſame thing: hee erreth, becauſe there be other religious vſes beſides worſhip: but, if he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them <hi>diſiunctiuely,</hi> as they ought to be taken; that is, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying diuers things, then he falcifieth the ſecond comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which ſaith onely; thou ſhalt not make it <hi>to bow down to it, nor worſhip it:</hi> but maketh no mention of other vſes; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſly, nor by way of implication; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſhould be contrary to himſelfe, which after this commandement was giuen; yet commanded images to be made for religious vſes, as the braſen Serpent, and the images which were in <hi>Slomons</hi> Temple, and ihe Cherubins vpon the mercy ſeate: ſo that theſe words; <hi>religious vſes,</hi> are an addition of his owne vnto Gods word. And, whereas he ſaith; <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>all occaſions and meanes leading to idolatry, are forbidden.</hi>
               </q> I anſwer; the Croſſe in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is no leading to idolatry; for as much as our doctrine concerning the vſe of it, is clearely ſet downe; that we put no confidence in it, &amp; our vſe of it is according to our doctrine: if he vſe it otherwiſe, it is his fault, &amp; not ours. Our doctrine and practiſe is as plaine to the contrary, as that of <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and halfe <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> concerning the altar which they crected, their doctrine explaining ther intent, &amp; their vſe of it being conſonant to their doctrine, remoued all ſcruples &amp; iealouſie out of the minds of their brethren, which before were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſo concerning that point they were well ſatisfied, as alſo our brethren woulde bee concerning this controuerſie, were they as charitably minded towards vs, being Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as the Iewes were towards their brethren being Iewes. Therefore, where he ſaith: wee offend againſt St. <hi>Iohns</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, warning vs to <hi>keepe our ſelues from idolls;</hi> becauſe we doe vſe an idoll in the ſeruice of God. I anſwer as before, it is <hi>petitio principij.</hi> a begging of the queſtion: for I haue ſhewed, how it is no idoll, and hee is greatly deſtitute of a <hi>medius terminus,</hi> to proue that concluſion which hee vndertooke to proue. If we grant all Croſſes which are worſhipped, to be idolls: it cannot follow, that our Croſſe in Baptiſme which is not worſhipped, is an idoll, no more then this: that becauſe all altars, erected for ſacrifice in places prohibited of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10643:37"/> God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were abhomination, therfore the altar of which before I ſpake, being not ercted for that end, was alſo abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Neither doth he ſo fitly alleage for his purpoſe, that our Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Homily <hi>againſt perill of idolatry,</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the remouing of images out of churches, which were ſet vp by Papiſts to be worſhipped, and are worſhipped, to prooue that by the ſame reaſon, the Croſſe in Baptiſme al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Proteſtants; ſhould be alſo abrogated, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was appointed for worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor yet worſhipped. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that place of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alleaged againſt images <note place="margin">
                  <hi>August. in Pſal.</hi> 113.</note> which haue <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>eyes, eares, noſes, which doe valere ad curuandum infaelicem animum, depraue the minde of man, which is very apt to be deluded and carried away, and alſo are an obiect to the eye, very dangerous to intice and allure to idolatry:</hi>
               </q> fitly applied by him to the ſigne of the Croſſe, not viſible, not permanent, and of which, none of theſe things may be verified, which are incident to the images which haue eyes, eares, and noſes. And for our part, we doe as much abhorre ſuch, both images and image-makers, as this author doth, or as euer <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> did, whom he citeth, how vnproperly ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And to anſwer the concluſion, which ſo idlely he infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vpon theſe authorities: That, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>if godly fathers were ſo vehement againſt erecting images of Chriſt and Saints, euen at that time, before any worſhip was giuen vnto them: much more would they withſtand it now, after men haue made idolls of them:</hi> and therefore hee condemneth vs for <hi>induring the idoll of the Croſſe</hi> (as he calleth it) <hi>in the ſeruice and ſacraments of God, and contrary to</hi> Dauids <hi>doctrine, keeping an honourable memory of that which the Prophet</hi> Eſay <hi>willeth vs to abandon.</hi>
               </q> I ſay, it is no meruaile though they were ſo vehement againſt erecting <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>Eſa</hi> 50, 22</note> of images in Churches, for we are as vehement in that cauſe as they were, and it behoued them at that time to be vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſidering that the whole world then was giuen to idolatry, and in euery citie the Pagans had their Temples, and as they worſhipped idolls in their paganiſme, ſo they were prone to worſhippe images after their conuerſion to the Chriſtian religion. And ſeeing they which were not conuerted, were readie to offer ſacrifice to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 13</note>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:10643:37"/> then aliue: no doubt but they would haue worſhipped their images when they were dead. But all this is vnfitly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To come to the MINOR, in which he indeuoureth to proue that the Croſse is an idoll.</head>
               <p>HE writeth for a marginall note in capitall letters, <hi>THE PROOFE OF THE MINOR:</hi> becauſe in his owne conceit it is already proued. But for the proofe of it, he onely alleageth the authority of <hi>Bellarmine, Potiformus, Hart, Costerus, Aquinas,</hi> being Papiſts, which hold that the ſigne of the Croſſe is to bee worſhipped with diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and aſcribe to it diuine power. And grant all this to be true, that the Papiſts worſhip the Croſſe, &amp; aſcribe ſo much to it. I anſwer as before, it toucheth not our ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme, which aſcribe no ſuch thing vnto it. Therfore nothing is here alleaged by him for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>MINOR,</hi> which is not already by vs anſwered and refuted ſufficiently, in the confutation of the <hi>MAIOR.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The author now commeth to his <hi>Ob: &amp; Sol:</hi> and in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe obiecteth, that our Croſſe is <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> numero ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> vſu, the ſame Croſſe which was among the Papiſts, neither yet vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs as it was vſed among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>
                  </q> The validity of this obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our behalfe, wee ſhew to be of as great validity on our ſide, as it was for the tribes of <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and halfe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> on their ſide, which being chalenged by their brethren for ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of idolatry whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they erected an altar, which as it was not <hi>numero,</hi> ſo they anſwered it was not <hi>vſu,</hi> ſuch an altar as they ſuſpected it to be: which anſwer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented the Iews, &amp; might as well ſatisfy our brethren, if they were as charitable.</p>
               <p>But let vs examine the anſwer he maketh to this obiection. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>When</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>God commanded his people to breake downe the images of the heathen, and to extinguiſh the very name of them, they could not haue performed that charge, if they had burnt all the idolls of</hi> Canaan, <hi>and made others new of the ſame forme, though to another vſe not idolatrous: ſo cannot we diſcharge our</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:10643:38"/> 
                     <hi>duties, if hauing defaced the Popiſh idolls, wee erect them new in our Church, though not to worſhip; becauſe it cannot be without breach of the commandement: Babes, keep your ſelues from idolls.</hi>
                  </q> So farre diſputeth the maker of the <hi>ſyllogiſme,</hi> in our behalfe. But, becauſe it may be verified of vs, which was ſaide of the blinde man who receiued his ſight; <hi>aetatem habet, prò ſe reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat,</hi> we are old enough to anſwer for our ſelues; we will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer our own ſelues for our ſelues, we craue no helpe of our aduerſary, but we will ſhew the vnſufficiency of this anſwer two maner of waies. Firſt, he hath dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed from his matter, becauſe the ſubiect of this diſputation is an humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance become an idoll, whereas he inſtanceth in humane or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which are not become idolls, but which originally were idolls, and erected by infidells to this end, that they ſhould be worſhipped: for that was to the imitation of the heathen people, &amp; this is not ſo. And, according to this kinde of diſputation, he might as well impoſe a neceſſity vpon vs, of ſuppreſſing all our pariſh Churches, as the Browniſts do; becauſe they were not onely the Popes ordinance, but alſo ordeined for the celebration of the Maſſe, and ſo imployed from their firſt erection, vntill this late reformation of the Church. For, according to Gods commandement, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the idolls their ſelues were to bee put downe, but alſo the altars, groues, and high places, where the idolatry was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and the Prieſts which did offer the ſacrifices, all they being abhominable as the idoll it ſelfe. Secondly, in that he taketh it <hi>pro conceſſo,</hi> as a thing granted, that the Croſſe is an idoll, it is but a begging of the queſtion, as before I haue ſhewed; becauſe it is not yet proued, that the ſigne of the croſſe is an idol among vs: neither doth it follow, that if with the Papiſts it were ſo; therfore with vs it is ſo, no more then becauſe their bread in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is an idol, therfore ours is alſo an idoll. That only <hi>numero</hi> which is worſhipt is an idol; for <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  </hi> author co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, <hi>wher there is no worſhip ther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no idol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we may proceede farther. For as much as the ſigne of the Croſſe, like the bread in the Lords Supper, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was free from ſuperſtition, &amp; the abuſe of it which grew after, is remoued by vs, why may not the one continue
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10643:38"/> among vs as well as the other without any ſuch ſlanderous imputation of idolatry? His anſwer is; <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>becauſe one is an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinance, and the other diuine, as the braſen ſerpent which being an humane ardinance when it was abuſed, was defaced by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias.</hi>
                  </q> To which wee reply, that neither the ſigne of the Croſſe is an humane ordinance, as before wee haue ſhewed, neither might an humane ordinance bee vſed though not an idoll, by his own doctrine, neither an idoll, though at the firſt it were a diuine ordinance, neither was that braſen ſerpent an humane ordinance, as by the text it appeareth: For the Lord ſaid to Moſes, <hi>make thee a ſerpent, and ſet it vp for a ſigne, that as many as are bitten may looke vpon it, and liue; So</hi> Moſes <hi>made a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb:</hi> 21. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>of Braſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And, whereas he alledgeth out of Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: <hi>horum ſi legem poſtules ſcripturarum, nullam inuenies,</hi> that we haue no warrant out of the Scripture; it is to be vnderſtood that according to <hi>Tertullian</hi> we haue no expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of holy writ to vſe the ſigne of the Croſſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in baptiſme, and therefore we hold it as a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, whether it be vſed or omitted, yet we haue an example of ſigning with the ſigne of the croſſe out of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> as I haue alledged, to ſhew that man is not the firſt deuiſer of it, but that man followeth gods example: ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> albeit we haue not <hi>legem aut praecaptum,</hi> a law or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement to impoſe vpon vs the vſe of the croſſe, yet we haue an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to ſhew that God was the firſt author of it. And againe, <hi>authoritas in negatiuis non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,</hi> it followeth not that becauſe the Scriptures make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> his father, therefore hee had no father: or becauſe the Scriptures commend <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for a iuſt man, and make no mention of his ſinnes, that therefore he had no ſinnes as <hi>Rodolphus Agricola</hi> in his <hi>Topics</hi> obſerueth out of <hi>S. Auguſtin.</hi> All things neceſſarie to ſaluation, are expreſly ſet downe in the holy Scriptures, but this is a matter indifferent, &amp; no way concerning the ſtate of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Now he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth with his coleworts twice ſodden, &amp; repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that which he hath ſo often ſaid before: that <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>the croſſe is become an idoll, and therefore not fit to be vſed in the ſeruice of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa,</hi>
                  </q> which becauſe it is but a tautalogy, or repetition of the ſame thing, I refer this obiection to the anſwere made before.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10643:39"/> And farther, to preſſe vs with more vnthruthes, hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth that it is <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>retained among vs with opinion very ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and erroneous, becauſe in our</hi> 30. <hi>Canon eccleſiaſticall, wee read theſe words: That the child is dedicated by it, to the ſeruice of him that dyed vpon the croſſe, which</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is to equal the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man, with the ordinance of God, to aſcribe that vnto the Croſſe which is due vnto Baptiſme, ſuch an abſurditie, as no water can cleanſe it.</hi>
                  </q> To which I anſwere: that which cannot be waſhed away by water, may bee auoided by diſtinction.There are two ſortes of dedication to the ſeruice of him that died vpon the Croſſe, one actiue, the other ſignificatiue, action is due to Baptiſme, but ſignification after the act is ended, is aſcribed to the ſigne of the Croſſe, becauſe the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Baptiſme dedicateth them, and the ſigning of the Croſſe ſignifieth, that they are already dedicated vnto that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, but there is the difference betweene the work it ſelfe, and the declaration or teſtifying of the worke after it is finiſhed, when Baptiſme being ended, we make a ſolemne declaration of it vnto the people. Farther, this ſyllogiſer ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>we vſe not the ſigne of the Croſſe as Auguſtine, Cyprian, and Chryſoſtome did, which vſed it to conſecrate the elements, and not to croſſe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but referred that to the Biſhoppes confirmation,</hi>
                  </q> as if wee were neceſſarily tyed to followe their example, or as, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did that, we might not doe this, or as if becauſe they did that, therefore they did not this: or as if the ſigne of the Croſſe were not as effectual to liuing children which are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body of Chriſt, as to dead elements to whom the merits of the Croſſe &amp; ſufferings of Chriſt doe no way ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine: or as if it were not as lawfull for the miniſter to vſe the croſſe in baptiſme, as it was for the Biſhop to vſe it in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, or the ſigne were leſſe effectuall in the one then in the other. But, let vs examine his proofes by which he confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his aſſertion, that the Fathers vſed not the croſſe in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Firſt he ſaith by way of anticipation, that this place of Tertullian: <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>The fleſh is waſhed, that the ſoule may be purged: the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">De reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restione caruis.</note> 
                     <hi>fleſh is annointed, that the ſoule may be conſecrated: the fleſh is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the ſoule may be guarded, may as wel be referred to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation as to Baptiſme.</hi> 
                  </q>And, I retort it againe vpon him,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10643:39"/> that it may be as indifferently vnderſtood, of baptiſme as of confirmation. But ſaith he: <hi>the fathers deſcribing the forme of baptiſme did make no mention of it in baptiſme.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <note place="margin">Martyr in defens: ad Antoninu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tertul: de Baptiſmo, et coronâ mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis.</note> that the Croſſe is no part of the forme or eſſence of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but onely the word and the element, neither is it vſed vntill the ſacrament be finiſhed, and therefore no meruaile though deſcribing the forme of baptiſme they made no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Croſſe, therefore this negatiue argument cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the vſe of the Croſſe. And yet, that the Fathers did vſe to ſigne them with the Croſſe which were baptized, it is euident by their owne words: for <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith in theſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dè coronâ cap:</hi> 3.</note> termes: <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>ad omnem progreſſum atquè promotum, ad omnem aditum atqùe exitum, ad veſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tum, ad calciatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ad lauacra, ad meu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, ad lumina, ad cubilia, ad ſedilia, quaecun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nos conuerſatio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercet, frontem crucis ſignaculo terimus,</hi>
                  </q> that in his time, at their goings out &amp; commings in, when they put on their clothes, their ſhooes. when they waſh or eate, or light the candle, at their lying downe, or ſitting vp, whatſoeuer they doe, they ſigne their forheads with the ſigne of the Croſſe. And <hi>Cyril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Hieroſolymit</hi> ſaith: <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Non pudeat igitur nos crucifixum confiteri,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cyrillus</note> 
                     <hi>ſed in fronte confidentèr ſignaculum crucis digitis imprimatur, &amp; in alijs omnibus crux fiat.</hi>
                  </q> That wee may not be aſhamed to confeſſe Chriſt crucified, we ſigne our forheads confidently, and in all other actions we make the Croſſe. And S. <hi>Iero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſaith: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heiron: Epiſt:</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Ad omnem actum &amp; progreſſuus manus crucem pingit,</hi>
                  </q> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we doe we make a Croſſe. The concluſion followeth out of their aſſertions, that if in their dayes, in all actions the croſſe was vſed and the forheads ſigned, then a Croſſe was made vpon their forheads which were Baptized.</p>
               <p>As for our ſigning with the Croſſe, we doe it after Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is finiſhed, to ſhew that we adde nothing to Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; that we thinke ſo honourably of that ordinance, that it needeth no addition, to cleare our ſelues of that iniuſt imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is laid vpon vs, of adding vnto it. And therefore, whereas hee alledgeth that the praying and croſſing are one continuall action of the adminiſtration of the Sacrament, and that by our ſelues the Croſſe is called <hi>ſignum crucis in Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme. I anſwer: Baptiſme is
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10643:40"/> taken two manner of waies, for the ſacrament it ſelfe, ſimply and barely conſidered in its own nature &amp; eſſence, conſiſting onely of the element and word, and as in the holy Scriptures it is ſet down &amp; comended vnto vs, &amp; ſo <hi>Signum crucis eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà</hi> the ſigne of the Croſſe is no part of baptiſme, nor any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition vnto it: or elſe it is taken, <hi>Prò ſacrame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â cùm ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis baptiſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>itantibus,</hi> for the action, together with all ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath appointed for the celebritie of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; ſo, not onely the Croſſe, but alſo the prayers which are vſed, and preaching, which are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are <hi>extra baptiſmum,</hi> no part of baptiſme, and yet may be called <hi>preces lectae in baptiſmo,</hi> prayers which are read in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and ſo <hi>concio habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a in baptiſmo,</hi> a Sermon made at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, ſo <hi>crux in baptiſmo</hi> the Croſſe in Baptiſme, though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them are held for any part of Baptiſme, and therefore by them no violence is offred to the diuine ordinance.</p>
               <p>We conclude, This ſigning with the ſigne of the Croſſe, hath beene commended to vs from antiquitie of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, to ſhew that it is not a noueltie of 60. yeares old, as this ſyllogiſer hath obiected, neither doe we alledge anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie as though we did grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon bare antiquitie without reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but we alledg antiquity againſt the nouelty of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſlaunder vs, ſhewing that antiquitie in points of Religion is to be preferred before nouelty. And, to his reply which aſketh <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>why we doe not alſo giue vnto them which are Baptized, milke &amp; hony? why we doe not vſe the ſigne of the Croſſe with opinion of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and efficacy as the ancient Fathers did? and aſcribe that vnto it which antiquitie did?</hi>
                  </q> I anſwer: the argument doth not follow that, becauſe we doe <hi>colliger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vuas,</hi> gather grapes: therfore we may not <hi>cauerespinas,</hi> take heed of being pricked with thorns, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21.</note> but we muſt firſt by the Apoſtles rule <hi>omnia probare</hi> proue all things, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>quod benum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct tenere</hi> retaine that which is good. And if ther be any which <hi>think baptiſme vnauailable without the croſſe, inſomuch as that they rebaptize when the croſſe is omitted,</hi> as this ſyllogiſme maker alledgeth, the fault is in their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not in our religion, which teach the contrary by our canons, and puniſh ſuch offenders by our lawes.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:10643:40"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
